<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <teiHeader type="text">
            <fileDesc>
                  <titleStmt>
                        <title>The Speech on the Embassy from Speeches (English). Machine readable
                              text</title>
                        <author>Aeschines</author>
                        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                        <respStmt>
                              <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                              <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                              <name>William Merrill</name>
                              <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                              <name>David Smith</name>
                        </respStmt>
                        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

                  </titleStmt>
                  <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                  </publicationStmt>
              

                  <sourceDesc>
                        <biblStruct>
                              <monogr>
                                    <author>Aeschines</author>
                                    <title>Aeschines with an English translation by Charles Darwin
                                          Adams, Ph.D.</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press;
                                                London, William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                                          <date>1919</date>
                                    </imprint>
                              </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                  </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
            <encodingDesc>
                  <refsDecl>
                        <refState unit="speech"/>
                        <refState unit="section"/>
                  </refsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
            <profileDesc>
                  <langUsage>
                        <language ident="en">English</language>
                        <language ident="greek" usage="100">Greek</language>
                  </langUsage>
            </profileDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                  <!--
                  <change>
                        <date>April 1992</date>
                        <respStmt>
                              <name>David Smith</name>
                              <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                        </respStmt>
                        <item>SGML markup</item>
                  </change>
                  <change><date>5/26/09</date><respStmt><name>RS</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt>
                       <item>  
$Log: aeschin_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-10-07 21:00:38  rsingh04
began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:02:02  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/18 20:11:04  rsingh04
changed bibl references to perseus:abo to the abbreviation for more uniformity

Revision 1.12  2009/06/05 20:27:19  rsingh04
removed all the spacing before the log keyword because it is really really picky

Revision 1.10  2009/06/04 14:22:33  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.9  2009/05/27 15:55:16  rsingh04
added cvs log keyword
                              
                        </item>
                  </change>
                  
            <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
                  <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            </revisionDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      <text xml:lang="en">
            <body>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I beg you, fellow citizens, to hear me
                              with willing and friendly mind, remembering how great is my peril, and
                              how many the charges against which I have to defend myself;
                              remembering also the arts and devices of my accuser, and the cruelty
                              of the man who, speaking to men who are under oath to give equal
                              hearing to both parties, had the effrontery to urge you not to listen
                              to the voice of the defendant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                        <p> and it was not anger that made him say it; for no man who is lying is
                              angry with the victim of his calumny, nor do men who are speaking the
                              truth try to prevent the defendant from obtaining a hearing; for the
                              prosecution does not find justification in the minds of the hearers
                              until the defendant has had opportunity to plead for himself and has
                              proved unable to refute the charges that have been preferred.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                        <p> But Demosthenes, I think, is not fond of fair argument, nor is that the
                              sort of preparation he has made. No, it is your anger that he is
                              determined to call forth. And he has accused me of receiving bribes—he
                              who would be the last man to make such suspicion credible! For the man
                              who seeks to arouse the anger of his hearers over bribery must himself
                              refrain from such conduct.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But, fellow citizens, as I have listened
                              to Demosthenes' accusation, the effect upon my own mind has been this:
                              never have I been so apprehensive as on this day, nor ever more angry
                              than now, nor so exceedingly rejoiced. I was frightened, and am still
                              disturbed, lest some of you form a mistaken judgment of me, beguiled
                              by those antitheses of his, conceived in deliberate malice. And I was
                              indignant—fairly beside myself at the charge, when he accused me of
                              insolence and drunken violence towards a free woman of <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">Demosthenes in his speech (<bibl n="Dem. 19.196"
                                          >Dem. 19.196</bibl> ff.) had told in detail the story of
                                    the abuse of a well-born Olynthian captive by Aeschines and
                                    others at a banquet in <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                                          >Macedonia</placeName>.</note> But I was rejoiced when, as
                              he was dwelling on this charge, you refused to listen to him. This I
                              consider to be the reward that you bestow upon me for a chaste and
                              temperate life.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                        <p> To you I do, indeed, give praise and high esteem for putting your faith
                              in the life of those who are on trial, rather than in the accusations
                              of their enemies; however, I would not myself shrink from defending
                              myself against this charge. For if there is any man among those who
                              are standing outside the bar—and almost the whole city is in the
                              court—or if there is any man of you, the jurors, who is convinced that
                              I have ever perpetrated such an act, not to say towards a free person,
                              but towards any creature, I hold my life as no longer worth the
                              living. And if as my defence proceeds I fail to prove that the
                              accusation is false, and that the man who dared to utter it is an
                              impious slanderer, then, even though it be clear that I am innocent of
                              all the other charges, I declare myself worthy of death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But strange indeed did that other argument
                              of his seem to me, and outrageously unjust, when he asked you whether
                              it was possible in one and the same city to sentence Philocrates to
                              death because he would not await trial and so condemned himself, and
                              then to acquit me. But I think that on this very ground I ought most
                              certainly to be cleared for if the man who condemns himself by not
                              awaiting trial is guilty, certainly he who denies the charge and
                              submits his person to the laws and to his fellow citizens is not
                              guilty.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now, fellow citizens, as regards the rest
                              of his accusations, if I pass over any point and fail to mention it, I
                              beg of you to question me and let me know what it is that you wish to
                              hear about, and to refrain from forming any judgment in advance, but
                              to listen with impartial goodwill. I do not know where I ought to
                              begin, so inconsistent are his accusations. See whether you think I am
                              being treated in a reasonable way.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                        <p> it is I who am now on trial, and that too for my life; and yet the
                              greater part of his accusation has been directed against Philocrates
                              and Phrynon and the other members of the embassy, against Philip and
                              the peace and the policies of Eubulus; it is only as one among all
                              these that he gives me a place. But when it is a question of
                              solicitude for the interests of the state, one solitary man stands out
                              in all his speech—Demosthenes; all the rest are traitors! For he has
                              unceasingly insulted us and poured out his slanderous lies, not upon
                              me alone, but upon all the rest as well.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="section">
                        <p> and after treating a man with such contempt, later, when it suits his
                              whim, he turns about, and as though he were accusing an Alcibiades or
                              a Themistocles, the most famous men among all the Greeks, he proceeds
                              to charge that same man with having destroyed the cities in <placeName
                                    key="tgn,4003963">Phocis</placeName>, with having lost you the
                              Thracian coast, with having expelled from his kingdom Cersobleptes, a
                              friend and ally of the city.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="section">
                        <p> and he undertook to liken me to Dionysius, the tyrant of <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, and vehemently and with
                              loud cries he called upon you to be on your guard against me; and he
                              related the dream of the priestess in <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
                                    >Sicily</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Neither
                                    the comparison with Dionysius nor the story of the dream was
                                    retained by Demosthenes when he revised his speech for
                                    publication.</note> Then, after all this exaggeration, he
                              begrudged me the credit even for what he had slanderously charged me
                              with accomplishing, and ascribed it all, not to my words, but to the
                              arms of Philip.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When now a man has shown such trickery and
                              effrontery, it is difficult even to remember every single thing, and
                              in the face of danger it is not easy to answer unexpected slanders.
                              But I will begin with those events which I think will enable me to
                              make my presentation most clear and intelligible to you, and fair;
                              these events are the discussion that took place concerning the peace,
                              and the choice of the ambassadors. In this way I shall best remember
                              his charges and best be able to speak effectively, and you will be
                              best instructed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>There is one thing, at any rate, which I
                              think you all yourselves remember: how the ambassadors from <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, after they had discussed
                              with our assembly the question of our making peace with them, told us
                              that Philip also had asked them to report to you that he wished to
                              come to terms and be at peace with you. Not long after this, Phrynon
                              of Rhamnus was captured by privateers, during the Olympian truce,
                              according to his own complaint.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                                    >Shortly before the time for the Olympic festival in each
                                    quadrennium, heralds were sent out by the Elean state to carry
                                    to all Greeks the invitation to the festival and to proclaim a
                                    sacred truce between all warring Greek states. Phrynon claimed
                                    that Macedonian pirates had violated this truce.</note> Now when
                              he had been ransomed and had come home, he asked you to choose an
                              envoy to go to Philip in his behalf, in order that, if possible, he
                              might recover his ransom money. You were persuaded, and chose
                                    <placeName key="tgn,6001610">Ctesiphon</placeName> as envoy for
                              him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="section">
                        <p> When <placeName key="tgn,6001610">Ctesiphon</placeName> returned from
                              his mission, he first reported to you on the matters for which he was
                              sent, and then in addition he said that Philip declared that he had
                              gone to war with you against his own will, and that he wished, even
                              now, to be rid of the war. When <placeName key="tgn,6001610"
                                    >Ctesiphon</placeName> had said this and had also told of the
                              marked kindness of his reception, the people eagerly accepted his
                              report and passed a vote of praise for <placeName key="tgn,6001610"
                                    >Ctesiphon</placeName>. Not a voice was raised in opposition.
                              Then it was, and not till then, that Philocrates of Hagnus offered a
                              motion, which was passed by unanimous vote of the people that Philip
                              be allowed to send to us a herald and ambassadors to treat for peace.
                              For up to this time even that had been prevented by certain men who
                              made it their business to do so, as the event itself proved.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="section">
                        <p> for they attacked the motion as unconstitutional,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">On the indictment for proposing an
                                    unconstitutional measure, see <bibl n="Aeschin. 3">Aeschin.
                                          3</bibl>, Introduction.</note> subscribing the name of
                              Lycinus to the indictment, in which they proposed a penalty of one
                              hundred talents. When the case came to trial Philocrates was ill, and
                              called as his advocate Demosthenes, not me. And Demosthenes the
                              Philip-hater came to the platform and used up the day in his plea for
                              the defence. Finally Philocrates acquitted, and the prosecutor failed
                              to receive the fifth part of the votes.<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">A prosecutor who failed to receive one-fifth
                                    part of the votes of the jury was subject to a fine of 1,000
                                    drachmas and disability to bring such a suit in the
                                    future.</note> This is matter of common knowledge.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="section">
                        <p> Now about the same time <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus"
                                    >Olynthus</placeName> was taken, and many of our citizens were
                              captured there, among them Iatrocles, brother of Ergochares, and
                              Eueratus, son of Strombichus. Their families naturally made
                              supplication in their behalf, and begged you to provide for them.
                              Their spokesmen before the people were Philocrates and Demosthenes,
                              not Aeschines. So Aristodemus the actor is sent as envoy to Philip, as
                              being an acquaintance of his, and of a profession that naturally wins
                              friends.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="section">
                        <p> But when Aristodemus returned from his mission, his report to the senate
                              was delayed by certain business of his, and meanwhile Iatrocles came
                              back from <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, released
                              by Philip without ransom. Then many people were angry with Aristodemus
                              for having failed to make his report, for they heard from Iatrocles
                              the same story about Philip.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The same
                                    story that the Euboean ambassadors and <placeName
                                          key="tgn,6001610">Ctesiphon</placeName> had brought, that
                                    Philip was ready to discuss peace.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="section">
                        <p> Finally Democrates of <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna"
                                    >Aphidna</placeName> went before the senate and persuaded them
                              to summon Aristodemus. One of the senators was Demosthenes, my
                              accuser! Aristodemus appeared before them, reported Philip's great
                              friendliness toward the city, and added this besides, that Philip even
                              wished to become an ally of our state. This he said not only before
                              the senate, but also at an assembly of the people. Here again
                              Demosthenes spoke no word in opposition, but even moved that a crown
                              be conferred on Aristodemus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Next Philocrates moved that ten
                              ambassadors be chosen to go to Philip and discuss with him both the
                              question of peace and the common interests of the Athenians and
                              Philip. At the election of the ten ambassadors I was nominated by
                              Nausicles, but Philocrates himself nominated Demosthenes—Demosthenes,
                              the man who now accuses Philocrates.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="section">
                        <p> and so eager was Demosthenes for the business, that in order to make it
                              possible for Aristodemus to be a member of our embassy without
                              financial loss to himself, he moved that we elect envoys to go to the
                              cities in which Aristodemus was under contract to act, and beg in his
                              behalf the cancelling of his forfeitures. To prove the truth of this,
                              take, if you please, the decrees, and read the deposition of
                              Aristodemus, and call the witnesses before whom the deposition was
                              made, in order that the jury may know who was the good friend of
                              Philocrates, and who it was that promised to persuade the people to
                              bestow the rewards on Aristodemus.<quote type="Decrees"
                                          ><title>Decrees</title></quote><quote type="Deposition"
                                          ><title>Deposition</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The whole affair, therefore, from the
                              beginning originated not with me, but with Demosthenes and
                              Philocrates. And on the embassy he was eager to belong to our mess—not
                              with my consent, but with that of my companions, Aglaocreon of
                              Tenedos, whom you chose to represent the allies, and Iatrocles. And he
                              asserts that on the journey I urged him to join me in guarding against
                              the beast—meaning Philocrates. But the whole story was a fabrication;
                              for how could I have urged Demosthenes against Philocrates, when I
                              knew that he had been Philocrates' advocate in the suit against the
                              legality of his motion, and that he had been nominated to the embassy
                              by Philocrates?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="section">
                        <p> Moreover, this was not the sort of conversation in which we were
                              engaged, but all the way we were forced to put up with Demosthenes'
                              odious and insufferable ways. When we were discussing what should be
                              said, and when Cimon remarked that he was afraid Philip would get the
                              better of us in arguing his claims, Demosthenes promised fountains of
                              oratory, and said that he was going to make such a speech about our
                              claims to <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>
                              and the origin of the war that he would sew up Philip's mouth with an
                              unsoaked rush,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The job would be so
                                    easy that he would not have to stop to soak the rush fiber and
                                    make it pliable. A proverbial expression.</note> and he would
                              persuade the Athenians to permit Leosthenes to return home,<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Leosthenes was an Athenian orator
                                    and general, who had been condemned to death in 361 because of
                                    the failure of his campaign in the northern waters; he was now
                                    in exile in <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>.
                                    The recovery of <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                                          >Amphipolis</placeName> would mollify the anger of the
                                    Athenians against him</note> and Philip to restore <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName> to <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But not to describe at length the
                              overweening self-confidence of this fellow, as soon as we were come to
                                    <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, we arranged
                              among ourselves that at our audience with Philip the eldest should
                              speak first, and the rest in the order of age. Now it happened that
                              the youngest man of us was, according to his own assertion,
                              Demosthenes. When we were summoned—and pray now give especial
                              attention to this, for here you shall see the exceeding enviousness of
                              the man, and his strange cowardice and meanness too, and such
                              plottings against men who were his own fellow ambassadors and his
                              messmates as one would hardly enter into even against his bitterest
                              enemies. For you remember he says<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See
                                          <bibl n="Dem. 19.189">Dem. 19.189</bibl> ff. Aeschines had
                                    protested that Demosthenes, in attacking his fellow-ambassadors
                                    on their return from <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                                          >Macedonia</placeName>, was violating the common decencies
                                    of life, which demanded that men who had sat at table together
                                    should treat one another as friends. Demosthenes replied that
                                    the table and the salt, even, in the case of the prytanes and
                                    other high officials who ate together at a common official
                                    table, gave no immunity to the wrongdoer; his fellow-officials
                                    were free to bring him to punishment. If the public table of the
                                    prytanes did not protect the guilty from attack by his
                                    fellow-officers, the table and the salt of the group of
                                    ambassadors should be no protection to Aeschines against
                                    Demosthenes' attack.</note> it is the salt of the city and the
                              table of the state for which he has most regard—he, who is no citizen
                              born—for I will out with it!—nor akin to us.<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">In <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.171">Aeschin.
                                          3.171</bibl> f., Aeschines declares that the maternal
                                    grandmother of Demosthenes was a Scythian.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="section">
                        <p> But we, who have shrines and family tombs in our native land, and such
                              life and intercourse with you as belong to free men, and lawful
                              marriage, with its offspring and connections, we while at <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> were worthy of your
                              confidence, or you would never have chosen us, but when we had come to
                                    <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> we all at
                              once turned traitors! But the man who had not one member of his body
                              left unsold, posing as a second Aristeides “the Just,” is displeased,
                              and spits on us, as takers of bribes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Hear now the pleas that we made in your
                              behalf, and again those which stand to the credit of Demosthenes, that
                              great benefactor of the state, in order that I may answer one after
                              another and in full detail each one of his accusations. But I commend
                              you exceedingly, gentlemen of the jury, that in silence and with
                              fairness you are listening to us. If, therefore, I fail to refute any
                              one of his accusations, I shall have myself, not you, to blame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>So when the older men had spoken on the
                              object of our mission, our turn came.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                                    >The turn of Aeschines and Demosthenes as the youngest of the
                                    ambassadors.</note> All that I said there and Philip's reply, I
                              reported fully in your assembly in the presence of all the citizens,
                              but I will try to recall it to you now in a summary way.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="section">
                        <p> In the first place, I described to him our traditional friendship and
                              your generous services to Amyntas, the father of Philip, recalling
                              them all one after another, and omitting nothing. Secondly, I reminded
                              him of services of which he himself had been both witness and
                              recipient. For shortly after the death of Amyntas, and of Alexander,
                              the eldest of the brothers, while Perdiccas and Philip were still
                              children, when their mother Eurydice had been betrayed by those who
                              professed to be their friends,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="section">
                        <p> and when Pausanias was coming back to contend for the throne,<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Amyntas, king of <placeName
                                          key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, left three sons,
                                    Alexander, Perdiccas, and Philip. Alexander succeeded his
                                    father, but after a short reign he was assassinated. His mother
                                    Eurydice with her paramour Ptolemaeus took the throne. Her power
                                    was threatened by Pausanias, a member of a rival princely
                                    house.</note> an exile then, but favoured by opportunity and the
                              support of many of the people, and bringing a Greek force with him,
                              and when he had already seized Anthemon, <placeName key="tgn,7011182"
                                    >Therma</placeName>, Strepsa, and certain other places, at a
                              time when the Macedonians were not united, but most of them favoured
                              Pausanias: at this crisis the Athenians elected Iphicrates as their
                              general to go against <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                                    >Amphipolis</placeName>—for at that time the people of
                              Amphipolis were holding their city themselves and enjoying the
                              products of the land.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="section">
                        <p> When Iphicrates had come into this region—with a few ships at first, for
                              the purpose of examining into the situation rather than of laying
                              siege to the city— “Then,” said I, “your mother Eurydice sent for him,
                              and according to the testimony of all who were present, she put your
                              brother Perdiccas into the arms of Iphicrates, and set you upon his
                              knees—for you were a little boy—and said, ‘Amyntas, the father of
                              these little children, when he was alive, made you his son,<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Amyntas, hard pressed by his
                                    Illyrian and Thessalian neighbors, had at one time been driven
                                    from his throne by a rival prince. After two years he was
                                    restored to power by the help of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
                                          >Sparta</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                          >Athens</placeName>. It is conjectured that this was the
                                    occasion of his adoption of the Athenian Iphicrates, one of the
                                    most capable leaders of mercenary troops.</note> and enjoyed the
                              friendship of the city of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                    >Athens</placeName>; we have a right therefore to consider you
                              in your private capacity a brother of these boys, and in your public
                              capacity a friend to us.’</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="section">
                        <p> After this she at once began to make earnest entreaty in your behalf and
                              in her own, and for the maintenance of the throne—in a word for full
                              protection. When Iphicrates had heard all this, he drove Pausanias out
                              of <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> and preserved
                              the dynasty for you.” Next I spoke about Ptolemaeus, who had been made
                              regent, telling what an ungrateful and outrageous thing he had done: I
                              explained how in the first place he continually worked against our
                              city in the interest of <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                                    >Amphipolis</placeName>, and when we were in controversy with
                              the Thebans, made alliance with them; and then how Perdiccas, when he
                              came to the throne, fought for <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                                    >Amphipolis</placeName> against our city.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="section">
                        <p> And I showed that, wronged as you were, you maintained your friendly
                              attitude; for I told how, when you had conquered Perdiccas in the war,
                              under the generalship of Callisthenes, you made a truce with him, ever
                              expecting to receive some just return. And I tried to remove the ill
                              feeling that was connected with this affair by showing that it was not
                              the truce with Perdiccas that led the people to put Callisthenes to
                              death, but other causes. And again I did not hesitate to complain of
                              Philip himself, blaming him for having taken up in his turn the war
                              against our state.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="section">
                        <p> As proof of all my statements, I offered the letters of the persons in
                              question, the decrees of the people, and Callisthenes' treaty of
                              truce. Now the facts about our original acquisition both of the
                              district and of the place called Ennea Hodoi,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">Ennea Hodoi ( “Nine Roads”) was the old name of
                                    the place colonized by the Athenians in 436 under the name of
                                          <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                                    >Amphipolis</placeName>.</note> and the story of the sons of
                              Theseus, one of whom, Acamas, is said to have received this district
                              as the dowry of his wife—all this was fitting to the occasion then,
                              and was given with the utmost exactness, but now I suppose I must be
                              brief; but those proofs which rested, not on the ancient legends, but
                              on occurrences of our own time, these also I called to mind.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="section">
                        <p> For at a congress<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The “Congress of
                                          <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>,” 371
                                    b.c.</note> of the Lacedaemonian allies and the other Greeks, in
                              which Amyntas, the father of Philip, being entitled to a seat, was
                              represented by a delegate whose vote was absolutely under his control,
                              he joined the other Greeks in voting to help <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to recover possession of
                                    <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>. As
                              proof of this I presented from the public records the resolution of
                              the Greek congress and the names of those who voted.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="section">
                        <p> “Now,” said I, “a claim which Amyntas renounced in the presence of all
                              the Greeks, and that not by words alone, but by his vote, that claim
                              you his son have no right to advance. But if you argue that it is
                              right for you to keep the place because you took it in war, if it is
                              true that it was a war against us in which you took the city, you do
                              hold it justly, by right of conquest; but if it was from the
                              Amphipolitans that you took a city which belonged to the Athenians, it
                              is not the property of the Amphipolitans that you are holding, but
                              territory of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.”<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                                          >Amphipolis</placeName> was founded as a colony of
                                          <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in 436,
                                    and became one of the most important cities on the northern
                                    coast. The Spartans seized it early in the Peloponnesian war,
                                    and held it till the close of the war. They then renounced their
                                    claim to it, but the people of the city themselves refused to
                                    return to Athenian allegiance. Repeated expeditions were sent
                                    out by the Athenians to retake the city, but without success.
                                    One of Philip's first acts was to seize <placeName
                                          key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>. It was
                                    claimed at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>
                                    that he had promised, if given a free hand, to restore the place
                                    to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; but this
                                    he refused to do, and so began the first war between <placeName
                                          key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and Philip. The
                                    Athenian claim to the city was therefore one of the most
                                    important matters to be presented by the ambassadors whose
                                    mission Aeschines is here describing.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now when I had said this and more beside,
                              at last came Demosthenes' turn to speak. All were intent, expecting to
                              hear a masterpiece of eloquence. For, as we learned afterwards, his
                              extravagant boasting had been reported to Philip and his court. So
                              when all were thus prepared to listen, this creature mouthed forth a
                              proem—an obscure sort of thing and as dead as fright could make it;
                              and getting on a little way into the subject he suddenly stopped
                              speaking and stood helpless; finally he collapsed completely.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="section">
                        <p> Philip saw his plight and bade him take courage, and not to think, as
                              though he were an actor on the stage, that his collapse was an
                              irreparable calamity, but to keep cool and try gradually to recall his
                              speech, and speak it off as he had prepared it. But he, having been
                              once upset, and having forgotten what he had written, was unable to
                              recover himself; nay, on making a second attempt, he broke down again.
                              Silence followed; then the herald bade us withdraw.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now when we were by ourselves, our worthy
                              colleague Demosthenes put on an exceedingly sour face and declared
                              that I had ruined the city and the allies. And when not only I, but
                              all the rest of the ambassadors were amazed, and asked him his reason
                              for saying that, he asked me if I had forgotten the situation at
                                    <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and if I did
                              not remember that the people were worn out and exceedingly anxious for
                              peace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="section">
                        <p> “Or does your confidence rest,” said he, “on those fifty ships that have
                              been voted but are never going to be manned? You have so exasperated
                              Philip by the speech you have made that the effect of it could not
                              possibly be to make peace out of war, but implacable war out of
                              peace!” I was just beginning to answer him, when the attendants
                              summoned us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When we had come in and taken our seats,
                              Philip began at the beginning and undertook to make some sort of
                              answer to every argument which we had advanced. Naturally he dwelt
                              especially on my argument, for I think I may fairly say that I had
                              omitted nothing that could be said; and again and again he mentioned
                              my name in the course of his argument. But in reply to Demosthenes,
                              who had made such a laughing.stock of himself, not one word was said
                              on a single point, I believe. And you may be sure that this was pain
                              and anguish to him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="section">
                        <p> But when Philip turned to expressions of friendship, and the bottom
                              dropped out of the slander which this Demosthenes had previously
                              uttered against me before our fellow ambassadors, that I was going to
                              be the cause of disagreement and war, then indeed it was plain to see
                              that he was altogether beside himself, so that even when we were
                              invited to dinner he behaved with shameful rudeness.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When we set out on our return home after
                              completing our mission, suddenly he began talking to each of us on the
                              way in a surprisingly friendly manner. Why, up to that time I had
                              never so much as known the meaning of words like “kerkops,” or the
                              so-called “paipalema,” or “palimbolon”<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">We are as ignorant of the particular shades of
                                    vulgarity and rascality conveyed by these words as Aeschines
                                    says he was before his initiation.</note> but now after
                              acquiring him as expounder of the mysteries of all rascality, I am
                              fully instructed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="section">
                        <p> and he would take each of us in turn to one side, and to one he would
                              promise to open a subscription to help him in his private
                              difficulties, and to another that he would get him elected general. As
                              for me, he fol- lowed me about, congratulating me on my ability and
                              praising my speech; so lavish was he in his compliments that I became
                              sick and tired of him. And when we were all dining together at
                                    <placeName key="tgn,7010894">Larisa</placeName>, he made fun of
                              himself and the embarrassment which had come upon him in his speech,
                              and he declared that Philip was the most wonderful man under the
                              sun.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="section">
                        <p> When I had added my testimony, saying something like this, that Philip
                              had shown excellent memory in his reply to what we had said, and when
                                    <placeName key="tgn,6001610">Ctesiphon</placeName>, who was the
                              oldest of us, speaking of his own advanced age and the number of his
                              years, added that in all his many years he had never looked upon so
                              charming and lovable a man, then this Sisyphus<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">A proverbial name for a cheat.</note> here
                              clapped his hands and said,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="section">
                        <p> “But, Ctesiphon, it will never do for you to tell the people that, nor
                              would our friend here,” meaning me, “venture to say to the Athenians
                              that Philip is a man of good memory and great eloquence.” And we
                              innocently, not foreseeing the trick of which you shall hear
                              presently, allowed him to bind us in a sort of agreement that we would
                              say this to you.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Demosthenes dared
                                    them to do it; they accepted the challenge and wagered that they
                                    would.</note> And he begged me earnestly not to fail to tell how
                              Demosthenes also said something in support of our claim to <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now up to this point I am supported by the
                              testimony of my colleagues in the embassy, whom he has reviled and
                              slandered from beginning to end of his accusation. But his words on
                              the platform in your presence you yourselves have heard; so it will
                              not be possible for me to misrepresent them. And I beg of you to
                              continue to hear patiently the rest of my narrative. I do not forget
                              that each of you is anxious to hear the story of Cersobleptes and the
                              charges made about the Phocians, and I am eager to get to those
                              subjects; but you will not be as well able to follow them unless you
                              shall first hear all that preceded. And if, in my peril, you allow me
                              to speak as I wish, you will be able to save me, if I am innocent, and
                              that on good and sufficient grounds; and you will also have before you
                              the facts that are acknowledged as you proceed to examine the points
                              that are in dispute.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>On our return, then, after we had rendered
                              to the senate a brief report of our mission and had delivered the
                              letter from Philip, Demosthenes praised us to his colleagues in the
                              senate, and he swore by Hestia, goddess of the senate,<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The hearth of the Prytaneum, the
                                    headquarters of the standing committee of the senate, was
                                    regarded as the common hearth of the state; a statue of Hestia
                                    was in this hall, and in the senate-house was an altar of that
                                    goddess.</note> that he congratulated the city on having sent
                              such men on the embassy, men who in honesty and eloquence were worthy
                              of the state.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="section">
                        <p> In referring to me he said something like this: that I had not
                              disappointed the hopes of those who elected me to the embassy. And to
                              cap it all he moved that each of us be crowned with a garland of wild
                              olive because of our loyalty to the people, and that we be invited to
                              dine on the morrow in the Prytaneum. To prove that I have spoken to
                              you nothing but the truth, please let the clerk take the decree, and
                              let him read the testimony of my colleagues in the embassy.<quote
                                    type="Decree"><title>Decree</title></quote><quote
                                    type="Testimony"><title>Testimony</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now when we presented the report of our
                              embassy before the assembly, <placeName key="tgn,6001610"
                                    >Ctesiphon</placeName> came for ward first and spoke, including
                              in his account the points that he was to make according to his
                              agreement with Demosthenes, I mean about Philip's social
                              accomplishments, his personal appearance, and his doughty deeds at the
                              cups. Next Philocrates and Dercylus spoke briefly; then I came
                              forward.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="48" type="section">
                        <p> After giving an account of our mission in general, I went on to say,
                              according to the agreement with my colleagues on the embassy, that
                              Philip showed both memory and eloquence when he spoke. And I did not
                              forget what Demosthenes had asked me to mention, namely, that we had
                              agreed that he was to speak about <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                                    >Amphipolis</placeName>, in case any point should have been
                              passed over by the rest of us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="49" type="section">
                        <p> After we had spoken, last of all Demosthenes arose, and with that
                              imposing air of his, and rubbing his forehead, when he saw that the
                              people approved my report and were satisfied with it, he said that he
                              was amazed at both parties, as well the listeners as the ambassadors,
                              for they were carelessly wasting time—the listeners wasting the time
                              for taking counsel, the ambassadors the time for giving it, all of
                              them amusing themselves with foreign gossip, when they ought to be
                              giving attention to our own affairs; for nothing, he said, was easier
                              than to render account of an embassy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="50" type="section">
                        <p> “I wish,” said he, “to show you how the thing ought to be done.” As he
                              said this he called for the reading of the decree of the people. When
                              it had been read he said, “This is the decree according to which we
                              were sent out; what stands written here, we did. Now, if you please,
                              take the letter that we have brought from Philip.” When this had been
                              read he said, “You have your answer; it remains for you to
                              deliberate.”</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="51" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The people shouted, some applauding his
                              forceful brevity, but more of them rebuking his abominable jealousy.
                              Then he went on and said, “See how briefly I will report all the rest.
                              To Aeschines Philip seemed to be eloquent, but not to me; nay, if one
                              should strip off his luck and clothe another with it, this other would
                              be almost his equal.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="52" type="section">
                        <p> To <placeName key="tgn,6001610">Ctesiphon</placeName> he seemed to be
                              brilliant in person, but to me not superior to Aristodemus the actor”
                              (he was one of us on the embassy). “One man says he has a great
                              memory; so have others. ‘He was a wonderful drinker’; our Philocrates
                              could beat him. One says that it was left to me to speak about our
                              claim to <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>;
                              but neither to you nor to me would this orator be capable of yielding
                              a moment of his time.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="53" type="section">
                        <p> all this talk of theirs,” said he, “is sheer nonsense. But for my part,
                              I am going to move that safe conduct be granted both for the herald
                              who has come from Philip, and for the ambassadors who are to come here
                              from him; also I shall move that on the arrival of the ambassadors the
                              prytanes call a meeting of the assembly for two successive days to
                              consider not only the question of peace, but the question of an
                              alliance also; and finally, that if we, the members of the embassy,
                              are thought to deserve the honor, a vote of thanks be passed, and an
                              invitation be given us to dine tomorrow in the prytaneum.”</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="54" type="section">
                        <p> is proof of the truth of what I say, take, if you please, the decrees,
                              that you, gentlemen of the jury, may know how crooked he is and how
                              jealous, and how completely he and Philocrates were in partnership in
                              the whole affair; and that you may know his character—how treacherous
                              and faithless. Call also my colleagues in the embassy, if you please,
                              and read their testimony.<quote type="Decrees"
                                    ><title>Decrees</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="55" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Moreover, he not only made these motions,
                              but afterwards he moved in the senate to assign seats in the theatre
                              for the Dionysia to the ambassadors of Philip when they should
                                    arrive.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">It had been expected
                                    that the ambassadors of Philip would arrive in time to take up
                                    their business before the Great Dionysia; the delay in their
                                    arrival necessitated postponing the business until after the
                                    festival, a period of about a week.</note> Read this decree
                                    also.<quote type="Decree"
                                    ><title>Decree</title></quote><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now
                              read also the testimony of my colleagues in the embassy, that you may
                              know, fellow citizens, that when it is a question of speaking in the
                              city's behalf, Demosthenes is helpless, but against those who have
                              broken bread with him and shared in the same libations, he is a
                              practised orator.<quote type="Testimony"
                                    ><title>Testimony</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="56" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You find, therefore, that it was not
                              Philocrates and I who entered into partnership in the negotiations for
                              the peace, but Philocrates and Demosthenes. And I think that the
                              proofs which I have presented to you in confirmation of what I have
                              said, are sufficient. For as to the report we made, you yourselves are
                              my witnesses; but I have presented to you my colleagues in the embassy
                              as witnesses of what was said in <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                                    >Macedonia</placeName> and of what took place in the course of
                              our journey. But you heard and remember the accusation which
                              Demosthenes made a few moments ago. He began with the speech which I
                              made in the assembly on the question of the peace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="57" type="section">
                        <p> and, utterly untruthful in this part of his accusation, he complained
                              bitterly about the occasion of that speech, saying that it was
                              delivered in the presence of the ambassadors whom the Greeks had sent
                              to you; for you had invited them in order that if you must go on with
                              the war, they might join you against Philip, and that if peace should
                              seem the better policy, they might participate in the peace. Now see
                              the man's deceit in a momentous matter, and his outrageous
                              shamelessness.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="58" type="section">
                        <p> For in the public archives you have the record of the dates when you
                              chose the several embassies which you sent out into <placeName
                                    key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, when the war between you
                              and Philip was still in progress, and also the names of the
                              ambassadors; and the men themselves are not in <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, but here in <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Now for embassies from
                              foreign states an opportunity to address the assembly of the people is
                              always provided by a decree of the senate. Now he says that the
                              ambassadors from the states of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                                    >Hellas</placeName> were present.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="59" type="section">
                        <p> Come forward, then, Demosthenes, to this platform while I have the
                              floor, and mention the name of any city of <placeName
                                    key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> you choose from which you
                              say the ambassadors had at that time arrived. And give us to read the
                              senatorial decrees concerning them from the records in the
                              senate-house, and call as witnesses the ambassadors whom the Athenians
                              had sent out to the various cities. If they testify that they had
                              returned and were not still abroad at the time when the city was
                              concluding the peace, or if you offer in evidence any audience of
                              theirs before the senate, and the corresponding decrees dated at the
                              time of which you speak, I leave the platform and declare myself
                              deserving of death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="60" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now read also what is said in the decree
                              of the allies,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A decree of the
                                    confederate synod, sitting in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                          >Athens</placeName>. The states referred to in the
                                    preceding paragraph were outside this Athenian league.</note> in
                              which it stands expressly written, “Whereas the people of the
                              Athenians are deliberating with regard to peace with Philip, and
                              whereas the ambassadors have not yet returned whom the people sent out
                              into <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> summoning the
                              cities in behalf of the freedom of the Hellenic states, be it decreed
                              by the allies that as soon as the ambassadors return and make their
                              report to the Athenians and their allies the prytanes shall call two
                              meetings of the assembly of the people according to law, and that in
                              these meetings the Athenians shall deliberate on the question of
                              peace; and whatever the people shall decide, be it voted that this
                              decision stand as the common vote of the allies.” Now please read the
                              decree of the synod.<quote type="Decree of the Synod"><title>Decree of
                                          the Synod</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="61" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now in contrast with this, read, if you
                              please, the decree moved by Demosthenes, in which he orders the
                              prytanes, after the celebration of the City Dionysia and the session
                              of the assembly in the precinct of Dionysus,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">A meeting regularly held at the close of the
                                    City Dionysia to act on any matters growing out of the conduct
                                    of the festival.</note> to call two meetings of the assembly,
                              the one on the eighteenth, the other on the nineteenth; for in thus
                              fixing the dates, he saw to it that the meetings of your assembly
                              should be held before the ambassadors from the states of <placeName
                                    key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> should have arrived.
                              Moreover, the decree of the allies, which I acknowledge I also
                              supported, prescribes that you deliberate concerning peace—nothing
                              more; but Demosthenes prescribes the subject of an alliance also. Read
                              them the decree.<quote type="Decree"><title>Decree</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="62" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You have heard both decrees; by them
                              Demosthenes is convicted of saying that the ambassadors were here,
                              when they were still abroad, and of having made void the decree of the
                              allies, when you wished to comply with it. For it was their judgment
                              that we should wait for the ambassadors from the other states of
                                    <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> but Demosthenes
                              is responsible for having prevented your waiting for them, not only by
                              his words, most shamelessly shifty of all men, but by his act and his
                              decree, in which he required us to make our decision immediately.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="63" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But he has said that at the first of the
                              two meetings of the assembly, after Philocrates had spoken, I then
                              arose and found fault with the resolution for peace which he had
                              introduced, calling it disgraceful and unworthy of the city; but that
                              again on the next day I spoke in support of Philocrates, and succeeded
                              in sweeping the assembly off its feet, persuading you to pay no
                              attention to those who talked of our fathers' battles and trophies,
                              and not to aid the Greeks.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="64" type="section">
                        <p> But that what he has laid to my charge is not only false, but a thing
                              that could not have happened, he himself shall furnish one proof, a
                              witness against himself; another proof all the Athenians shall
                              furnish, and your own memory; a third, the incredibility of the
                              charge; and the fourth, a man of repute, who is active in public
                              affairs, Amyntor, to whom Demosthenes exhibited the draft of a decree,
                              asking him whether he should advise him to hand it to the clerk, a
                              decree not contrary in its provisions to that of Philocrates, but
                              identical with it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="65" type="section">
                        <p> Now, if you please, take and read the decree of Demosthenes,<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This is not the draft of a decree
                                    just spoken of, but that decree in which Demosthenes had
                                    provided for the two meetings of the assembly.</note> in which
                              you will see that he has prescribed that in the first of the two
                              meetings of the assembly all who wish shall take part in the
                              discussion, but that on the next day the presiding officers shall put
                              the question to vote, without giving opportunity for debate—the day on
                              which he asserts that I supported Philocrates in the discussion.<quote
                                    type="Decree"><title>Decree</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="66" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You see that the decrees stand as they
                              were originally written, whereas the words of rascals are spoken to
                              fit the day and the occasion. My accuser makes two speeches out of my
                              plea before the assembly, but the decree and the truth make it one.
                              For if the presiding officers gave no opportunity for discussion in
                              the second meeting, it is impossible that I spoke then. And if my
                              policy was the same as that of Philocrates, what motive could I have
                              had for opposing on the first day, and then after an interval of a
                              single night, in the presence of the same listeners, for supporting?
                              Did I expect to gain honor for myself, or did I hope to help
                              Philocrates? I could have done neither, but would have got myself
                              hated by all, and could have accomplished nothing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="67" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But please call Amyntor of the deme
                              Herchia and read his testimony. First, however, I wish to go over its
                              contents with you: Amyntor in support of Aeschines testifies that when
                              the people were deliberating on the subject of the alliance with
                              Philip, according to the decree of Demosthenes, in the second meeting
                              of the assembly, when no opportunity was given to address the people,
                              but when the decrees concerning the peace and alliance were being put
                              to vote,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="68" type="section">
                        <p> At that meeting Demosthenes was sitting by the side of the witness, and
                              showed him a decree, over which the name of Demosthenes stood written;
                              and that he consulted him as to whether he should hand it to the
                              presiding officers to put to vote; this decree contained the terms on
                              which Demosthenes moved that peace and alliance he made, and these
                              terms were identical with the terms which Philocrates had moved. Now,
                              if you please, call Amyntor of the deme Herchia; if he does not come
                              hither voluntarily, serve summons upon him.<quote type="Testimony"
                                          ><title>Testimony</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="69" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You have heard the testimony, fellow
                              citizens. Consider whether you conclude that it is I whom Demosthenes
                              has accused, or whether on the contrary he has accused himself in my
                              name. But since he also misrepresents the speech that I made, and puts
                              a false construction on what was said, I have no disposition to run
                              away, or to deny a word that was then spoken; I am not ashamed of what
                              I said; on the contrary, I am proud of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="70" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But I wish also to recall to you the time
                              and circumstances of your deliberations. We went to war in the first
                              place over the question of <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                                    >Amphipolis</placeName>. In the course of the war our general
                              succeeded in losing seventy-five allied cities,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">Aeschines chooses to speak as though the war
                                    with Philip were one and the same with the other,
                                    contemporaneous war, in which a large part of the Athenian
                                    allies broke off from the naval league.</note> which Timotheus,
                              the son of <persName><foreName>Conon</foreName></persName>, had won
                              over and made members of the synod—I am determined, as you see, to
                              speak right out, and to seek safety in frank and truthful speaking; if
                              you are otherwise minded, do what you will with me; I cannot
                              prevaricate—</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="71" type="section">
                        <p> and a hundred and fifty triremes which he took from the dockyards he
                              failed to bring back, a story which the accusers of Chares are never
                              tired of telling you in the courts; and he spent fifteen hundred
                              talents, not upon his troops, hut upon his tricky officers, a Deiares,
                              a Deipyrus, a Polyphontes, vagabonds collected from all <placeName
                                    key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> (to say nothing of the
                              wages of his hirelings on the bema and in the popular assembly), who
                              were exacting from the wretched islanders a contribution of sixty
                              talents a year, and seizing merchant ships and Greek citizens on the
                              high seas.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="72" type="section">
                        <p> and instead of respect and the hegemony of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                                    >Hellas</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                    >Athens</placeName> had a name that stank like a nest of
                                    Myonnesian<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><foreign
                                          xml:lang="greek">*muonnh/sos</foreign>, “Mouse-island”,
                                    was a little island off the coast of <placeName
                                          key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>, notorious as a
                                    nest of pirates.</note> pirates. And Philip from his base in
                                    <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> was no longer
                              contending with us for <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                                    >Amphipolis</placeName>, but already for <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName>, Imbros, and Scyros, our
                              own possessions, while our citizens were abandoning the <placeName
                                    key="tgn,1012789">Chersonese</placeName>, the undisputed
                              property of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. And
                              the special meetings of the assembly which you were forced to hold, in
                              fear and tumult, were more in number than the regular meetings.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="73" type="section">
                        <p> The situation was so precarious and dangerous that Cephisophon of
                              Paeania, one of the friends and companions of Chares, was compelled to
                              make the motion that Antiochus, who commanded the dispatch boats,
                              should sail immediately and hunt up the general who had been put in
                              charge of our forces, and in case he should happen to find him
                              anywhere, should tell him that the people of <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> were astonished to learn
                              that Philip was on the way to the <placeName key="tgn,1012789"
                                    >Chersonese</placeName>, Athenian territory, while as to the
                              general and the force which they themselves had sent out, the
                              Athenians did not even know what had become of them. To prove that I
                              am speaking the truth, hear the decree and recall the facts of the
                              war, and then charge the peace, not to the ambassadors, but to the
                              commanders of our arms.<quote type="Decree"
                                    ><title>Decree</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="74" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Such was the situation of the city, such
                              the circumstances under which the debate on the peace took place. But
                              the popular speakers arose and with one consent ignored the question
                              of the safety of the state, but called on you to gaze at the Propylaea
                              of the Acropolis, and remember the battle of , <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, and the tombs and
                              trophies of our forefathers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="75" type="section">
                        <p> I replied that we must indeed remember all these, but must imitate the
                              wisdom of our forefathers, and beware of their mistakes and their
                              unseasonable jealousies; I urged that we should emulate the battle
                              that we fought at <placeName key="perseus,Plataea"
                              >Plataea</placeName>, the struggles off the shores of <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, the battles of Marathon
                              and <placeName key="perseus,Artemisium">Artemisium</placeName>, and
                              the generalship of Tolmides, who with a thousand picked men of the
                              Athenians fearlessly marched straight through the <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, the enemy's
                              country.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="76" type="section">
                        <p> But I urged that we should take warning from the Sicilian expedition,
                              which was sent out to help the people of Leontini, at a time when the
                              enemy were already in our own territory and Deceleia was fortified
                              against us; and that final act of folly, when, outmatched in the war,
                              and offered terms of peace by the Lacedaemonians, with the agreement
                              that we should hold not only <placeName key="tgn,7002681"
                                    >Attica</placeName>, but <placeName key="tgn,7011173"
                                    >Lemnos</placeName>, Imbros, and Scyros also, and retain the
                              constitutional democracy, the people would have none of it, but chose
                              to go on with a war that was beyond their powers. And Cleophon, the
                              lyre-maker, whom many remembered as a slave in fetters, who had
                              dishonourably and fraudulently got himself enrolled as a citizen, and
                              had corrupted the people by distribution of money,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true"><bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 28">Aristot. Const.
                                          Ath. 28</bibl> tells us that it was Cleophon who
                                    introduced the two obol donation from the treasury to provide a
                                    free seat in the theatre for every citizen who applied for it.
                                    This was the beginning of the Theorika, recognized in the time
                                    of Aeschines as one of the greatest abuses in the
                                    democracy.</note> threatened to take his knife and slit the
                              throat of any man who should make mention of peace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="77" type="section">
                        <p> Finally they brought the city to such a pass that she was glad to make
                              peace, giving up everything, tearing down her walls, receiving a
                              garrison and a Lacedaemonian governor, and surrendering the democracy
                              to the Thirty, who put fifteen hundred citizens to death without a
                              trial. I admit that I urged that we should guard against such folly as
                              that, and imitate the conduct shortly before described. For it was
                              from no stranger that I heard that story, but from him who is nearest
                              of all men to me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="78" type="section">
                        <p> for Atrometus our father, whom you slander, though you do not know him
                              and never saw what a man he was in his prime—you, Demosthenes, a
                              descendant through your mother of the nomad Scythians—our father went
                              into exile in the time of the Thirty, and later helped to restore the
                              democracy; while our mother's brother, our uncle Cleobulus, the son of
                              Glaucus of the deme Acharnae, was with Demaenetus of the family of the
                              Buzygae, when he won the naval victory over Cheilon the Lacedaemonian
                              admiral. The sufferings of the city were therefore a household word
                              with us, familiar to my ears.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="79" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But you find fault with my service as
                              ambassador to <placeName key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName> and my
                              speech before the Ten Thousand<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                                    national assembly of the Arcadians. Aeschines appeared before
                                    them in 348 in the attempt to counteract the work of Philip's
                                    agents among them.</note> there, and you say that I have changed
                              sides—yourself more slave than freeman, all but branded as a runaway!
                              So long as the war lasted, I tried so far as in me lay to unite the
                              Arcadians and the rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                                    >Hellas</placeName> against Philip. But when no man came to the
                              help of our city, but some were waiting to see what was going to
                              happen, and others were taking the field against us, while the
                              politicians in our own city were using the war to subsidize the
                              extravagance of their daily life,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For
                                    this use of <foreign xml:lang="greek">xorhgo/n</foreign> see the
                                    note on <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.240">Aeschin. 3.240</bibl> (<foreign
                                          xml:lang="greek">xorhgei=s</foreign>) of the Speech
                                    against <placeName key="tgn,6001610"
                                    >Ctesiphon</placeName>.</note> I acknowledge that I advised the
                              people to come to terms with Philip, and to make the peace, which you,
                              Demosthenes, now hold disgraceful, you who never had a weapon of war
                              in your hands—but which I declare to be much more honourable than the
                              war.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="80" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You ought, fellow citizens, to judge your
                              ambassadors in the light of the crisis in which they served your
                              generals, in the light of the forces which they commanded. For you set
                              up your statues and you give your seats of honour and your crowns and
                              your dinners in the Prytaneum, not to those who have brought you
                              tidings of peace, but to those who have been victorious in battle. But
                              if the responsibility for the wars is to he laid upon the ambassadors,
                              while the generals are to receive the rewards, the wars you wage will
                              know neither truce nor herald of peace, for no man will be willing to
                              be your ambassador.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="81" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now it remains for me to speak of
                              Cersobleptes and the Phocians, as well as the other matters in which I
                              have been slandered. For, fellow citizens, both on the first and on
                              the second embassy I reported to you what I saw, as I saw it; what I
                              heard, as I heard it. What was it then in either case: what was it
                              that I saw and what was it that I heard about Cersobleptes? I, as well
                              as all my colleagues in the embassy, saw the son of Cersobleptes a
                              hostage at Philip's court; and this is still the case.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="82" type="section">
                        <p> now it happened on the occasion of our first embassy, that at the moment
                              when I was leaving for home with the rest of the ambassadors, Philip
                              was setting out for <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>;
                              but we had his promise that while you were deliberating concerning
                              peace, he would not set foot on the <placeName key="tgn,1012789"
                                    >Chersonese</placeName> with an armed force. Now on that day
                              when you voted the peace, no mention was made of Cersobleptes. But
                              after we had already been elected to receive the oaths,<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The same ambassadors who had
                                    negotiated the preliminaries of the peace were appointed to go
                                    back to <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> and
                                    receive the ratification of the peace by Philip and his
                                    allies.</note> before we had set forth on the second embassy, an
                              assembly was held, the presidency of which fell by lot to
                                    Demosthenes,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A board of nine
                                    senators presided over the meetings of the assembly; one member
                                    of the board was chosen by lot as chief presiding officer for
                                    the day.</note> who is now accusing me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="83" type="section">
                        <p> in that assembly Critobulus of <placeName key="tgn,7002579"
                                    >Lampsacus</placeName> came forward and said that Cersobleptes
                              had sent him, and he demanded that he should be allowed to give his
                              oath to the ambassadors of Philip, and that Cersobleptes be enrolled
                              among your allies.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The peace that had
                                    just been negotiated was to be between Philip and his allies,
                                    and <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and her
                                    allies. By the allies of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                          >Athens</placeName> were meant the members of the Athenian
                                    naval league, whose synod, sitting at <placeName
                                          key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, had ratified in
                                    advance whatever action the Athenian people might take as to the
                                    peace. Cersobleptes was not a member of this league, but sought
                                    to be admitted at the last moment, in order to gain the
                                    protection of the peace. Demosthenes, feeling that his admission
                                    would endanger the success of the negotiations for peace,
                                    attempted to prevent his admission, by insisting on the
                                    irregularity of the procedure; Cersobleptes should have
                                    presented his credentials to the senate and obtained from them a
                                    resolution advising the assembly to hear his plea; and this
                                    should have been done at an earlier meeting.</note> When he had
                              thus spoken, Aleximachus of the deme Pelex handed to the presiding
                              officers a motion to be read, in which it was written that the
                              representative of Cersobleptes be permitted to join the other allies
                              in giving the oath to Philip.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="84" type="section">
                        <p> When the motion had been read—I think you all remember this—Demosthenes
                              arose from among the presiding officers and refused to put the motion
                              to vote, saying that he would not bring to naught the peace with
                              Philip, and that he did not recognize the sort of allies who joined
                              only in time, as it were, to help in pouring the peace libations; for
                              they had had their opportunity at an earlier session of the assembly.
                              But you shouted and called the board of presidents to the platform,
                              and so against his will the motion was put to vote.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="85" type="section">
                        <p> To prove that I am speaking the truth, please call Aleximachus, the
                              author of the motion, and the men who served with Demosthenes on the
                              board of presidents, and read their testimony.<quote type="Testimony"
                                          ><title>Testimony</title></quote><milestone unit="para"
                                    ed="P"/>You see, therefore, that Demosthenes, who just now burst
                              into tears here at mention of Cersobleptes, tried to shut him out of
                              the alliance. Now on the adjournment of that session of the assembly,
                              Philip's ambassadors proceeded to administer the oaths to your allies
                              in your army-building.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="86" type="section">
                        <p> and my accuser has dared to tell you that it was I who drove Critobulus,
                              Cersobleptes' ambassador, from the ceremony—in the presence of the
                              allies, under the eyes of the generals, after the people had voted as
                              they did! Where did I get all that power? How could the thing have
                              been hushed tip? If I had really dared to undertake such a thing,
                              would you have suffered it, Demosthenes? Would you not have filled the
                              market-place with your shouts and screams, if you had seen me, as you
                              just now said you did, thrusting the ambassador away from the
                              ceremony? But please let the herald call the generals and the
                              representatives of the allies, and do you hear their testimony.<quote
                                    type="Testimony"><title>Testimony</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="87" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Is it not, therefore, an outrage,
                              gentlemen, if one dares utter such lies about a man who is his own—no,
                              I hasten to correct myself, not his own, but your—fellow citizen, when
                              he is in peril of his life? Wisely, indeed, did our fathers prescribe
                              that, in the trials for bloodshed which are held at the
                                    Palladion,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This court was for
                                    cases of unintentional homicide.</note> the one who wins his
                              case must cut in pieces the sacrificial flesh, and take a solemn oath
                              (and the custom of your fathers is in force to this day), affirming
                              that those jurors who have voted on his side have voted what is true
                              and right, and that he himself has spoken no falsehood; and he calls
                              down destruction upon himself and his household, if this be not true,
                              and prays for many blessings for the jurors. A right provision, fellow
                              citizens, and worthy of a democracy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="88" type="section">
                        <p> For if no one of you would willingly defile himself with justifiable
                              bloodshed, surely he would guard against that which was unjustifiable,
                              such as robbing a man of life or property or civil rights—such acts as
                              have caused some men to kill themselves, others to be put to death by
                              decree of the state. Will you then, fellow citizens, pardon me, if I
                              call him a lewd rascal, unclean of body, even to the place whence his
                              voice issues forth, and if I go on to prove that the rest of his
                              accusation about Cersobleptes is false on the face of it?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="89" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You have a practice which in my judgment
                              is most excellent and most useful to those in your midst who are the
                              victims of slander: you preserve for all time in the public archives
                              your decrees, together with their dates and the names of the officials
                              who put them to vote. Now this man has told you that what ruined the
                              cause of Cersobleptes was this: that when Demosthenes urged that we
                              should go to <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>, where
                              Cersobleptes was being besieged, and should solemnly call on Philip to
                              cease doing this thing, I, as leader of the ambassadors and
                              influential with you, refused, and sat down in Oreus, I and the rest
                              of the ambassadors, busy with getting foreign consulships for
                                    ourselves.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Athenian citizens
                                    were employed by foreign states to represent their interests at
                                          <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and aid
                                    their citizens there. Demosthenes asserted that the ambassadors
                                    were intent on getting such appointments for
                              themselves.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="90" type="section">
                        <p> Hear now the letter which Chares sent to the people at the time, saying
                              that Cersobleptes had lost his kingdom and that Philip had taken
                              Hieron Oros<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This was an important
                                    post on the Thracian coast, and had been held by an Athenian
                                    garrison, in the interest of Cersobleptes.</note> on the
                              twenty-fourth of Elaphebolion. And it was Demosthenes, one of the
                              ambassadors, who was presiding in the assembly here on the
                              twenty-fifth of that month.<quote type="Letter"
                                    ><title>Letter</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="91" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now not only did we delay all the rest of
                              that month, but it was Munichion<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                                    next month after Elaphebolion.</note> when we set out. As
                              witness of this I will present the senate, for there is a decree of
                              theirs which commands the ambassadors to set out in order to receive
                              the oaths. Please read the decree of the senate.<quote type="Decree"
                                          ><title>Decree</title></quote><milestone unit="para"
                                    ed="P"/>Now read also the date of the decree.<quote type="Date"
                                          ><title>Date</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="92" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You hear that the decree was passed on the
                              third of Munichion. How many days before I set out was it that
                              Cersobleptes lost his kingdom? According to Chares the general it
                              occurred the month before—that is, if Elaphebolion is the month next
                              before Munichion! Was it, then, in my power to save Cersobleptes, who
                              was lost before I set out from home? And now do you imagine that there
                              is one word of truth in his account of what was done in <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> or of what was done in
                                    <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>, when he gives
                              the lie to the senate-house and the public archives, and falsifies the
                              date and the meetings of the assembly?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="93" type="section">
                        <p> and is it true, Demosthenes, that you at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                    >Athens</placeName> tried to exclude Cersobleptes from the
                              treaty, but pitied him when you got to Oreus? And do you today accuse
                              me of having taken bribes, you who were once fined by the Senate of
                              the Areopagus for not prosecuting your suit for assault, that time
                              when you indicted your cousin Demomeles of Paeania for the cut on your
                              head that you gave yourself with your own hand?<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">The reference is to a family quarrel which grew
                                    out of the suit of the young Demosthenes against his
                                    guardian.</note> And do you put on airs before these jurymen, as
                              though they did not know that you are the bastard son of Demosthenes
                              the cutler?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A bastard in the sense
                                    that his mother was of a Scythian family, and so debarred from
                                    legitimate Athenian wedlock. See on <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.22"
                                          >Aeschin. 2.22</bibl>.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="94" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But you undertook to say that I at first
                              refused to serve on the embassy to the Amphictyons,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">The embassy was strictly to Philip, but as it
                                    was to deal largely with Amphictyonic business in the hands of
                                    Philip and allies of his who were in control of Amphictyonic
                                    affairs, Aeschines can speak of it as “to the
                                    Amphictyons.”</note> and later went on the embassy and was
                              guilty of misconduct, and you read the one decree and suppressed the
                                    other.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The reference is to
                                    events after the return of the second embassy. After their
                                    report was accepted, a third embassy was appointed to go to
                                    Philip, extending the peace and alliance to his descendants, and
                                    declaring that if the Phocians would not submit to the
                                    Amphictyons, the Athenians would take the field against them.
                                    Most of the men appointed on this third embassy had served on
                                    the other two. Demosthenes was nominated, but he refused to
                                    serve. Aeschines was elected, but finally on the plea of illness
                                    he was excused by the senate, and his brother was appointed to
                                    take his place. The embassy had gone only as far as <placeName
                                          key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> when they received
                                    the news that the Phocians had surrendered to Philip; they
                                    therefore immediately returned to <placeName
                                          key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. The Athenians now
                                    reappointed the same men, including Aeschines, to go to meet
                                    Philip. Aeschines, now recovered in health, went on this fourth
                                    embassy. Demosthenes (<bibl n="Dem. 19.126">Dem. 19.126</bibl>)
                                    falsely declares that he went without having been elected. For
                                    the whole story from Demosthenes' standpoint, see <bibl
                                          n="Dem. 19.121">Dem. 19.121-133</bibl>. In <bibl
                                          n="Dem. 19.172">Dem. 19.172</bibl>, Demosthenes betrays
                                    the fact that there really was a reelection for the fourth
                                    embassy, and so confirms Aeschines' statement.</note> I was,
                              indeed, chosen one of the ambassadors to the Amphictyons, and even as
                              I had shown myself zealous in reporting to you the embassy from which
                              I had returned, so now, although I was in poor health, I did not
                              refuse the new mission, but promised to serve, if I should have the
                              strength. But as the ambassadors were on the point of setting out, I
                              sent my brother and his son with my physician to the senate, not to
                              decline service for me</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="95" type="section">
                        <p> (for the law does not permit men who have been elected by the assembly
                              to decline before the senate), but merely to testify to my
                                    illness.<milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When now the ambassadors
                              had been informed of the fate of the Phocians, they returned, and a
                              meeting of the assembly was held. I had by this time recovered and was
                              present. When the people insisted that we who had been originally
                              elected should all go on with the embassy in spite of what had
                              happened, I thought it my duty to speak the truth to the
                                    Athenians.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, Aeschines
                                    felt that he ought now to say frankly that his health was such
                                    that he could not decline that service.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="96" type="section">
                        <p> and when I rendered account of my service on that embassy, you,
                              Demosthenes, preferred no charge, but you proceed against my conduct
                              on this embassy, the embassy that was appointed to receive the oaths.
                              As to this I will make a clear and just defence. For it serves you, as
                              it does all liars, to confuse the dates, but it serves me to give the
                              events in their order, beginning with our journey to receive the
                                    oaths.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Aeschines returns to the
                                    story of the second embassy.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="97" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>In the first place, of the ten ambassadors
                              (or rather eleven, counting the representative of the allies, who was
                              with us) not one was willing to mess with Demosthenes, when we set out
                              on the second embassy, nor even to lodge at the same inn with him as
                              we journeyed, whenever it could be avoided, for they had seen how he
                              had plotted against them all on the previous embassy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="98" type="section">
                        <p> Now not a word was said about making the journey along the Thracian
                                    coast;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The journey which
                                    Demosthenes, in the speech for the prosecution, had said ought
                                    to have been made in order to forestall Philip's conquests
                                    there.</note> for the decree did not prescribe any such journey,
                              but simply that we should receive the oaths and transact certain other
                              business, nor could we have accomplished anything if we had gone, for
                              Cersobleptes' fate had already been decided, as you heard a moment
                              ago; for there is not a word of truth in what he has said, but, at a
                              loss for any true charge, he resorts to these prodigious lies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="99" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>On the journey two attendants followed
                              him, carrying sacks of bedding; in one of the sacks, he assured us,
                              was a talent of silver; so that his colleagues were reminded of those
                              old nicknames of his; for the boys used to call him “Batalos,” he was
                              so vulgar and obscene then when he was growing out of boyhood and was
                              bringing against his guardians big lawsuits of ten talents each, he
                              was called “Argas”;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">“Batalos” has
                                    been thought to mean “stammerer,” or perhaps “mamma-baby” (see
                                          <bibl n="Aeschin. 1.126">Aeschin. 1.126</bibl> and 131),
                                    but that explanation would hardly fit this passage. We really
                                    have no knowledge as to the derivation of the word. “Argas” was
                                    the name of a venomous snake.</note> now, grown to manhood, he
                              has got also the name that we apply to rascals in general,
                              “Blackmailer.”</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="100" type="section">
                        <p> and he was going with the intention of ransoming the captives,<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Athenian citizens who had been
                                    captured at the fall of <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus"
                                          >Olynthus</placeName>, and were now in slavery in
                                          <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>.</note>
                              as he said, and as he has just now told you, although he knew that at
                              no time during the war had Philip exacted ransom-money for any
                              Athenian, and although he had heard all Philip's friends say that he
                              would release the rest also, if peace should be made. And he was
                              carrying one talent for many unfortunates—sufficient ransom for one
                              man, and not a very well to-do man at that!</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="101" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But when we reached <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> and found Philip
                              returned from <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>, we held
                              a meeting;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This was a private meeting
                                    of the Athenian ambassadors to discuss what they should say to
                                    Philip at the coming audience.</note> the decree under which we
                              were acting was read, and we went over the instructions that had been
                              given us in addition to the business of receiving the oaths. But
                              finding that no one mentioned the subjects that were most important,
                              and all were dwelling on minor matters, I spoke words which I must
                              repeat to you.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="102" type="section">
                        <p> and in heaven's name, gentlemen, even as you allowed my accuser to speak
                              as he himself chose, pray so continue to listen quietly to the defence
                              also, in the same manner in which from the beginning you have listened
                              during all my speech thus far. Well, as I just now intimated, fellow
                              citizens, at the meeting of the ambassadors I said that it seemed to
                              me that we were strangely ignoring the most important matter that the
                              people had entrusted to us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="103" type="section">
                        <p> “The reception of the oaths, the discussion of the other questions, and
                              the talk about the prisoners, all that sort of thing could have been
                              done, I think, if the city had entrusted it to some of its petty
                              servants and sent them. But to reach a right solution of the supreme
                              question, so far as that is in our power or Philip's,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">The supreme question of the hour was the
                                    settlement of the long continued Phocian war. Whether <placeName
                                          key="tgn,4003963">Phocis</placeName> was to be defeated
                                    and <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> given a
                                    dangerous increase of power depended in large measure on what
                                    action Philip and the Athenians should decide to take, either
                                    jointly or severally. The Athenians had been unable to persuade
                                    Philip's ambassadors to include the Phocians among the states to
                                    be protected by the peace, but it was hoped that these
                                    ambassadors from <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                          >Athens</placeName> would be able to persuade Philip
                                    himself to favour <placeName key="tgn,4003963"
                                          >Phocis</placeName> as against <placeName
                                          key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>.</note> this is
                              now a task for wise ambassadors. I mean,” said I, “the question of the
                              expedition to <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae"
                                    >Thermopylae</placeName>, which you see in course of
                              preparation. That I am not wide of the mark in this matter, I will
                              show you by weighty considerations.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="104" type="section">
                        <p> For ambassadors from <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>
                              are here, ambassadors from Lacedaemonia have arrived, and here are we
                              with a decree of the people in which it stands written, ‘The
                              ambassadors shall also negotiate concerning any other good thing that
                              may be within their power.’ All <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                                    >Hellas</placeName> is watching to see what is going to happen.
                              If now our people had thought it wise to speak out plainly to Philip,
                              bidding him strip the Thebans of their insolence, and rebuild the
                              walls of the Boeotian towns,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                                    small towns of <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>
                                    which had been subjugated by <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                                          >Thebes</placeName>, and were now supporting the Phocians
                                    in the hope of regaining their independence.</note> they would
                              have asked this of him in the decree. But as it is, by the obscurity
                              of their language they left open a way of retreat for themselves, in
                              case they should fail to persuade him, and they thought best to take
                              the risk its our persons.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="105" type="section">
                        <p> Men, therefore, who are ambitious to serve the state must not assume the
                              function of other ambassadors whom the Athenians could have sent
                              instead of us, and at the same time, on their own initiative, try to
                              avoid stirring up the hostility of the Thebans. Epameinondas was a
                              Theban, and he did not cower before the fame of the Athenians, but
                              spoke right out in the Theban assembly, saying that they must remove
                              the propylaea of the Acropolis of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                    >Athens</placeName> and set it up at the entrance to the
                              Cadmeia.”</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="106" type="section">
                        <p> As I was in the midst of these words, Demosthenes protested with a loud
                              voice, as all our colleagues know, for on top of all his other crimes
                              he is for the Boeotians. At any rate words like these came from him:
                              “This fellow is full of quarrelsomeness and rashness. For myself, I
                              confess that I am timid, that I fear danger from afar, but I protest
                              against embroiling the cities one with another; I hold it to be the
                              wise course that we ambassadors refrain from meddlesome conduct.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="107" type="section">
                        <p> Philip is setting out for <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae"
                                    >Thermopylae</placeName>; I cover my eyes. No man is going to
                              call me to account for the wars of Philip, but for what I say that I
                              ought not to say, or what I do that I was not instructed to do.” The
                              upshot of the matter was that the ambassadors, when asked for their
                              opinion man by man, voted that each of us should say what he thought
                              was to our interests. To show that I speak the truth, please call my
                              colleagues and read their testimony.<quote type="Testimony"
                                          ><title>Testimony</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="108" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Accordingly, fellow citizens, when the
                              ambassadors were assembled at <placeName key="perseus,Pella"
                                    >Pella</placeName>, and Philip had arrived, and the herald
                              called the ambassadors of the Athenians, we came forward, not in the
                              order of age, as in the former embassy—a procedure which found favour
                              with some, and which seemed to be in accord with the orderly way of
                              our city<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Athenian “way” in such
                                    matters is described in <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.2">Aeschin.
                                          3.2</bibl>.</note>—but in the way that was dictated by the
                              effrontery of Demosthenes. For he said that he was the youngest of
                              all, but declared that he could not yield the position of first
                              speaker, and would not permit a certain person—hinting at me—to take
                              possession of Philip's ears and leave the rest no chance to speak.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="109" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>He began his speech with certain
                              slanderous allusions to his colleagues, to the effect that not all of
                              us had come with the same end in view, nor were we all of one mind;
                              and then he proceeded to review his own previous services to Philip:
                              first, his defence of Philocrates' motion, when Philocrates, having
                              moved that Philip be permitted to send ambassadors to the Athenians to
                              discuss peace, was defendant on the charge of having made an
                              unconstitutional proposal; secondly, he read the motion of which
                              Demosthenes himself was author, to grant safe conduct to the herald
                              and ambassadors from Philip; and thirdly, the motion that restricted
                              the people's discussion of peace to appointed days.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="110" type="section">
                        <p> To the account he added a conclusion like this: that he had been the
                              first to put a curb on those who were trying to block the peace; that
                              he had done this, not by his words, but by fixing the dates. Then he
                              brought up another motion, the one which provided that the people
                              should discuss an alliance also; then, after that, the motion about
                              assigning the front seats at the Dionysia to Philip's ambassadors.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="111" type="section">
                        <p> He alluded also to the special attention he had shown them: the placing
                              of cushions, and certain watchings and vigils of the night, caused by
                              men who were jealous of him and wished to bring insult upon his
                              honourable name! And that utterly absurd story, whereat his colleagues
                              covered their faces for shame, how he gave a dinner to the ambassadors
                              of Philip; and how when they set out for home he hired for them some
                              teams of mules, and escorted them on horseback. For he did not hide in
                              the dark, as certain others do, but made an exhibition of his fawning
                              conduct.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="112" type="section">
                        <p> And finally he carefully corrected those other statements:<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The statements that his colleagues
                                    had made to the assembly on their return from the first embassy,
                                    as related in <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.47">Aeschin. 2.47</bibl> and
                                          <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.52">Aeschin. 2.52</bibl>.</note>“I did
                              not say that you are beautiful, for a woman is the most beautiful of
                              all beings; nor that you are a wonderful drinker, for that is a
                              compliment for a sponge, in my opinion; nor that you have a remarkable
                              memory, for I think such praise belongs to the professional sophist.”
                              But not to prolong the story, he said such things in the presence of
                              the ambassadors from almost the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                                    >Hellas</placeName>, that laughter arose such as you seldom
                              hear.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="113" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But when at last he stopped and there was
                              silence, I was forced to speak—after such an exhibition of
                              ill-breeding and such excess of shameful flattery. Necessarily, by way
                              of preface, I made a brief reply to his insinuations against his
                              colleagues, saying that the Athenians had sent us as ambassadors, not
                              to offer apologies in <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                                    >Macedonia</placeName> for ourselves, but as men adjudged by our
                              life at home to be worthy of our city.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="114" type="section">
                        <p> Then after speaking briefly on the subject of the oaths for which we had
                              come, I reviewed the other matters that you had entrusted to us. For
                              the eminent Demosthenes, for all his exceeding eloquence, had not
                              mentioned a single essential point. And in particular I spoke about
                              the expedition to <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae"
                                    >Thermopylae</placeName>, and about the holy places, and
                                    <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, and the
                              Amphictyons. I called on Philip to settle matters there, preferably
                              not with arms, but with vote and verdict; but if that should be
                              impossible (it was already evident that it was, for the army was
                              collected and on the spot), I said that he who was on the point of
                              deciding the fate of the holy places of our nation ought to give
                              careful thought to the question of piety, and to give attention to
                              those who undertook to give instruction as to our traditions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="115" type="section">
                        <p> At the same time I reviewed from the beginning the story of the founding
                              of the shrine, and of the first synod of the Amphictyons that was ever
                              held; and I read their oaths, in which the men of ancient times swore
                              that they would raze no city of the Amphictyonic states, nor shut them
                              off from flowing water either in war or in peace; that if anyone
                              should violate this oath, they would march against such an one and
                              raze his cities;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The city that has
                                    violated its Amphictyonic oath can no longer claim the
                                    protection of that oath.</note> and if any one should violate
                              the shrine of the god or be accessory to such violation, or make any
                              plot against the holy places, they would punish him with hand and foot
                              and voice, and all their power. To the oath was added a mighty
                              curse.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="116" type="section">
                        <p> When I had read all this, I solemnly declared that in my opinion it was
                              not right that we should overlook the fact that the cities in
                                    <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> were lying in
                                    ruins.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See on <bibl
                                          n="Aeschin. 2.104">Aeschin. 2.104</bibl>.</note> To prove
                              that they were Amphictyonic cities and thus protected by the oaths, I
                              enumerated twelve tribes which shared the shrine: the Thessalians,
                              Boeotians (not the Thebans only), Dorians, Ionians, Perrhaebi,
                              Magnetes, Dolopians, Locrians, Oetaeans, Phthiotians, Malians, and
                              Phocians. And I showed that each of these tribes has an equal vote,
                              the greatest equal to the least: that the delegate from <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Dorion">Dorion</placeName> and Cytinion has equal
                              authority with the Lacedaemonian delegates, for each tribe casts two
                              votes; again, that of the Ionian delegates those from <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Eretria">Eretria</placeName> and <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Priene">Priene</placeName> have equal authority
                              with those from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and
                              the rest in the same way.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="117" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now I showed that the motive of this
                              expedition was righteous and just; but I said that the Amphictyonic
                              Council ought to be convened at the temple, receiving protection and
                              freedom to vote,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Council had been
                                    unable to meet while the Phocians were holding the shrine.
                                    Aeschines would have Philip' s army occupy <placeName
                                          key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, and so restore
                                    the Amphictyons to their rights.</note> and that those
                              individuals who were originally responsible for the seizure of the
                              shrine ought to be punished—not their cities, but the individuals who
                              had plotted and carried out the deed; and that those cities which
                              surrendered the wrongdoers for trial ought to be held guiltless. “But
                              if you take the field and with your forces confirm the wrongdoing of
                              the Thebans,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If Philip should help
                                    the Thebans to subdue the Phocians, the confirmation of Theban
                                    control over the Boeotian cities would naturally follow, as it
                                    did in the event.</note> you will receive no gratitude from
                              those whom you help, for you could not possibly do them so great a
                              service as the Athenians once did, and they have no memory for that;
                              while you will be wronging those whom you leave in the lurch, and will
                              find them, not your friends in the future, but all the more your
                              enemies.”</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="118" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But not to waste time in reciting to you
                              now precisely what was spoken there, I will content myself with this
                              brief summary of it all. Fortune and Philip were masters of the issue,
                              but I, of loyalty to you and of the words spoken. My words were words
                              of justice, and they were spoken in your interest; the issue was not
                              according to our prayer, but according to Philip's acts. Who,
                              therefore, is it that deserves your approval? Is it the man who showed
                              no desire to do any good thing whatever, or the man who left undone
                              nothing that was in his power? But I now pass over many things for
                              lack of time.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="119" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>He said that I deceived you by saying that
                              within a few days <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>
                              would be humbled; and that I told about the Euboeans, how I had
                              frightened them, and that I led you on into empty hopes. But, fellow
                              citizens, let me tell you what it is that he is doing. While I was
                              with Philip I demanded—and when I returned to you I reported that I
                              thought it right—that <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                                    >Thebes</placeName> should be Boeotian, and not <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>, Theban. He asserts, not
                              that I reported this, but that I promised it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="120" type="section">
                        <p> And I told you that Cleochares of <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis"
                                    >Chalcis</placeName> said that he was surprised at the sudden
                              agreement between you and Philip, especially when we had been
                              instructed “to negotiate concerning any good thing that should be
                              within our power.” For he said the people of the small states, like
                              himself, were afraid of the secret diplomacy of the greater.
                              Demosthenes asserts, not that I related this fact, but that I promised
                              to hand over <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>! But I
                              had supposed that when the city was about to deliberate on matters of
                              supreme importance, no statement from any Hellenic source ought to be
                              ignored.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="121" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But he falsely declared that when he
                              wished to report the truth, he was hindered by me, together with
                              Philocrates—for he divided the responsibility in that case also. Now I
                              should like to ask you this: Has any ambassador sent out from
                                    <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> ever been
                              prevented from presenting to the people an official report of his
                              conduct? And if one had suffered such treatment and had been
                              repudiated by his colleagues, would he ever have made a motion that
                              they be given a vote of thanks and invited to dinner? But Demosthenes
                              on his return from the second embassy, in which he says that the cause
                              of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> was ruined, moved
                              the vote of thanks in his decree;</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="122" type="section">
                        <p> and not only that, but when I had reported to the people what I had said
                              about the Amphictyons and Boeotians, not briefly and rapidly as now,
                              but as nearly word for word as possible, and when the people heartily
                              applauded, I called upon him together with the other ambassadors, and
                              asked them whether my report was true, and identical with what I had
                              said to Philip; and when all my colleagues had testified and praised
                              me, after them all Demosthenes arose and said: No, I had not to-day
                              been speaking as I spoke there, but that I spoke twice as well there.
                              You who are going to give the verdict are my witnesses of this.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="123" type="section">
                        <p> and yet what better opportunity could he have had to convict me than to
                              do it then and there, if I was in any wise deceiving the city? You
                              say, Demosthenes, that while I was in a conspiracy against the city in
                              the first embassy, you were not aware of it, but that on the second
                              you found it out—the embassy in which we find you testifying to my
                              services! And while accusing me for my conduct on the first embassy,
                              you at the same time deny that you accuse me, and direct your
                              accusations against the embassy that was sent to take the oaths. And
                              yet if it is the peace you find fault with, it was you who moved to
                              add the alliance to it. And if Philip did at any point deceive the
                              city, his deception had to do with the peace, for he was maneuvering
                              for the precise form of peace that would serve his own advantage. But
                              it was the earlier embassy that offered the opportunity to accomplish
                              this; the second took place after the thing was already done.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="124" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>How he has deceived you—deceit is ever the
                              mark of the charlatan—see from his own words. He says that I went down
                              the Loedias river to Philip in a canoe by night, and that I wrote for
                              Philip the letter which came to you. For Leosthenes, who had been
                              exiled from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> through
                              the work of blackmailers, was not competent to write a clever letter—a
                              man whom some do not hesitate to rank next to Callistratus of
                                    <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName> as an able
                              orator!</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="125" type="section">
                        <p> and Philip himself was not competent, against whom Demosthenes was not
                              able to hold his own when he tried to speak in your behalf! nor Python
                              of <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>, a man who
                              takes pride in his ability as a writer! but, as it seems, the thing
                              required my help too! And you say that time and again I had private
                              interviews with Philip in the daytime, but you accuse me of paddling
                              down the river in the night—the need of a midnight letter was so
                              urgent!</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="126" type="section">
                        <p> But there is no truth in your story, as those who messed with me have
                              come to testify—Aglaocreon of <placeName key="perseus,Tenedos"
                                    >Tenedos</placeName> and latrocles the son of Pasiphon, with
                              whom I slept every night during the whole time, from beginning to end;
                              they know that I was never away from them a single night, nor any part
                              of a night. We present also our slaves and offer them for
                                    torture;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Slave testimony was
                                    accepted in the Athenian courts only when it was given, or
                                    offered, under torture.</note> and I offer to interrupt my
                              speech if the prosecution agree. The officer shall come in and
                              administer the torture in your presence, gentlemen of the jury, if you
                              so order. There is still time enough to do it, for in the
                              apportionment of the day eleven jars of water have been assigned to my
                                    defence.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A definite time,
                                    measured by the water clock, or clepsydra, was assigned to each
                                    side. How long a time would be occupied by the running of one
                                    amphora of water through the clepsydra, we have no means of
                                    knowing.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="127" type="section">
                        <p> If the slaves testify that I ever slept away from these messmates of
                              mine, spare me not, fellow citizens, but rise up and kill me. But if
                              you, Demosthenes, shall be convicted of lying, let this be your
                              penalty—to confess in this presence that you are a hermaphrodite, and
                              no free man. Please summon the slaves to the platform here, and read
                              the testimony of my colleagues.<quote type="Testimony"
                                          ><title>Testimony</title></quote><quote type="Challenge"
                                          ><title>Challenge</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="128" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Since now he does not accept the
                              challenge, saying that he would not rest his case on the testimony of
                              tortured slaves, please take this letter, which Philip sent. For a
                              letter that kept us busy writing all night long must obviously be full
                              of clever deception of the city.<quote type="Letter"
                                          ><title>Letter</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="129" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You hear, gentlemen, what he wrote: “I
                              gave my oath to your ambassadors and he has written the names of those
                              of his allies who were present, both the names of the representatives
                              themselves and of their states; and he says he will send to you those
                              of his allies who were not there in time. Does it seem to you that it
                              would have been beyond Philip's ability to write that in the daytime,
                              and without my help?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="130" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But, by heaven, the only thing,
                              apparently, that this man Demosthenes cares about, is to win applause
                              while he is on the platform but whether or not a little later he will
                              be considered the greatest scoundrel in <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                                    >Hellas</placeName>, for that he appears to care not a whit. For
                              how could one put any faith in a man who has undertaken to maintain
                              that it was not Philip's generalship, but my speeches, that enabled
                              Philip to get this side <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae"
                                    >Thermopylae</placeName>! And he gave you a sort of reckoning
                              and enumeration of the days during which, while I was making my report
                              on the embassy, the couriers of Phalaecus, the Phocian tyrant, were
                              reporting to him how matters stood in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                    >Athens</placeName>, while the Phocians, putting their trust in
                              me, admitted Philip this side <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae"
                                    >Thermopylae</placeName>, and surrendered their own cities to
                              him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="131" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now all this is the invention of my
                              accuser. It was fortune, first of all, that ruined the Phocians, and
                              she is mistress of all things; and secondly, it was the long
                              continuance of the ten years' war. For the same thing that built up
                              the power of the tyrants in <placeName key="tgn,4003963"
                                    >Phocis</placeName>, destroyed it also: they established
                              themselves in power by daring to lay hands on the treasures of the
                              shrine, and by the use of mercenaries they put down the free
                              governments; and it was lack of funds that caused their overthrow,
                              when they had spent all their resources on these mercenaries.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="132" type="section">
                        <p> the third cause of their ruin was mutiny, such as usually attends armies
                              which are poorly supplied with funds. The fourth cause was Phalaecus'
                              inability to foresee the future. For it was plain that the Thessalians
                              and Philip were going to take the field; and shortly before the peace
                              with you was concluded, ambassadors came to you from the Phocians,
                              urging you to help them, and offering to hand over to you Alponus,
                                    <placeName key="perseus,Thronion">Thronion</placeName>, and
                                    <placeName key="perseus,Nicaea">Nicaea</placeName>, the posts
                              which controlled the roads to <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae"
                                    >Thermopylae</placeName>.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="133" type="section">
                        <p> But when you had passed a decree that the Phocians should hand over
                              these posts to your general Proxenus, and that you should man fifty
                              triremes, and that all citizens up to the age of forty years should
                              take part in the expedition, then instead of surrendering the Posts to
                              Proxenus, the tyrants arrested those ambassadors of their own who had
                              offered to hand over the garrison posts to you and when your heralds
                              carried the proclamation of the sacred truce of the Mysteries,<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A provision for the safe conduct of
                                    all Greeks, who wished to attend the celebration of the lesser
                                    Eleusinian Mysteries, which took place in <placeName
                                          key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> in the spring.</note>
                              the Phocians alone in all <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                                    >Hellas</placeName> refused to recognize the truce. Again, when
                              Archidamus the Laconian was ready to take over those posts and guard
                              them, the Phocians refused his offer, answering him that it was the
                              danger from <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> that
                              they feared, not the danger at home.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="134" type="section">
                        <p> That was before you had come to terms with Philip; but on the very day
                              when you were discussing the question of the peace, the letter of
                              Proxenus was read to you, in which he said that the Phocians had
                              failed to hand over the posts to him; and on the same day the heralds
                              of the Mysteries reported to you that the Phocians alone in all
                                    <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> had refused the
                              sacred truce, and had, furthermore, arrested the ambassadors who had
                              been here. To prove that I am speaking the truth, please call the
                              heralds of the truce, and the envoys Callicrates and Metagenes, whom
                              Proxenus our general sent to the Phocians, and let the letter of
                              Proxenus be read.<quote type="Testimony"
                                    ><title>Testimony</title></quote><quote type="Letter"
                                          ><title>Letter</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="135" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The dates, fellow citizens, taken from the
                              public archives, have been read and compared in your hearing, and you
                              have heard the witnesses, who further testify that before I was
                              elected ambassador, Phalaecus the Phocian tyrant distrusted us and the
                              Lacedaemonians as well, but put his trust in Philip.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="136" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But was Phalaecus the only one who failed
                              to discern what the outcome was going to be? How stood public opinion
                              here? Were you not yourselves all expecting that Philip was going to
                              humble the Thebans, when he saw their audacity, and because he was
                              unwilling to increase the power of men whom he could not trust? And
                              did not the Lacedaemonians take part with us in the negotiations
                              against the Thebans, and did they not finally come into open collision
                              with them in <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> and
                              threaten them? Were not the Theban ambassadors themselves perplexed
                              and alarmed? And did not the Thessalians laugh at all the rest and say
                              that the expedition was for their own benefit?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="137" type="section">
                        <p> Did not some of' Philip's companions say explicitly to some of us that
                              Philip was going to reestablish the cities in <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>? Had not the Thebans
                              already, suspicious of the situation, called out all their reserves
                              and taken the field? And did not Philip, when he saw this, send a
                              letter to you calling upon you to come out with all your forces in
                              defence of the cause of justice? As for those who are now for war, and
                              who call peace cowardice, did they not prevent your going out, in
                              spite of the fact that peace and alliance had been made with Philip?
                              And did they not say that they were afraid he would take your soldiers
                              as hostages?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="138" type="section">
                        <p> Was it I, therefore, who prevented the people from imitating our
                              forefathers, or was it you, Demosthenes, and those who were in
                              conspiracy with you against the common good? And was it a safer and
                              more honourable course for the Athenians to take the field at a time
                              when the Phocians were at the height of their madness and at war with
                              Philip, with Alponus and <placeName key="perseus,Nicaea"
                                    >Nicaea</placeName> in their possession—for Phalaecus had not
                              yet surrendered these posts to the Macedonians—and when those whom we
                              were proposing to aid would not accept the truce for the Mysteries,
                              and when we were leaving the Thebans in our rear: or after Philip had
                              invited us, when we had already received his oaths and had an alliance
                              with him, and when the Thessalians and the other Amphictyons were
                              taking part in the expedition?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="139" type="section">
                        <p> Was not the latter opportunity far better than the former? But at this
                              later time, thanks to the combination of cowardice and envy in you,
                              Demosthenes, the Athenians brought in their property from the fields,
                              when I was already absent on the third embassy,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">See on <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.94">Aeschin.
                                          2.94</bibl>. This was, strictly speaking, the fourth
                                    embassy; but as it was appointed to do what had been entrusted
                                    to the third, and was made up of the same men, Aeschines speaks
                                    of it as the third.</note> and appearing before the assembly of
                              the Amphictyons<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The ambassadors to
                                    Philip, while not formally accredited to negotiate with the
                                    Amphictyonic Council, which Philip had called together to act on
                                    the punishment of the Phocians, were present at <placeName
                                          key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> during their
                                    meeting, and Aeschines addressed the Council. see <bibl
                                          n="Aeschin. 2.142">Aeschin. 2.142</bibl>.</note>—that
                              embassy on which you dare to say that I set out without having been
                              elected, although, enemy as you are to me, you have never to this day
                              been willing to prosecute me as having wrongly served on it; and we
                              may safely assume that this is not because you begrudge me bodily
                              pains and penalties.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="140" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When, therefore, the Thebans were
                              besieging him with their importunities, and our city was in confusion,
                              thanks to you, and the Athenian hoplites were not with him;<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.137"
                                          >Aeschin. 2.137</bibl>.</note> when the influence of the
                              Thessalians had been added to that of the Thebans, thanks to your
                              shortsightedness and because of the hostility to the Phocians which
                              the Thessalians had inherited from that ancient time when Phocians
                              seized and flogged the Thessalian hostages; and when, before my coming
                              and that of Stephanus, Dercylus, and the rest of the ambassadors,
                              Phalaecus already made terms and departed;</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="141" type="section">
                        <p> Then the people of <placeName key="tgn,7011034">Orchomenus</placeName>
                              were in exceeding fear, and had begged for peace, on condition that
                              their lives should be spared and they be allowed to go forth from
                                    <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>;<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName key="tgn,7011034"
                                          >Orchomenus</placeName> was one of the towns referred to
                                    in <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.104">Aeschin. 2.104</bibl>.</note> when
                              the Theban ambassadors were standing by, and when it was plain that
                              Philip was threatened with the hostility of the Thebans and
                              Thessalians: then it was that the cause was lost not from any fault of
                              mine, but thanks to your treachery, Demosthenes, and your hired
                              service to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. Of this
                              I think I can furnish important confirmation from what has actually
                              happened.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="142" type="section">
                        <p> For if there were any truth in these assertions of yours, the Boeotian
                              fugitives, for whose expulsion I was responsible, and the Phocian
                              exiles, whose restoration I prevented, would be accusing me now. But
                              as a matter of fact they ignore the misfortunes that have come upon
                              them, and satisfied with my loyalty to them, the Boeotian exiles have
                              held a meeting and chosen men to speak in my behalf; and from the
                              towns of <placeName key="tgn,4003963">Phocis</placeName> have come
                              ambassadors whose lives I saved when I was representing you before the
                              Amphictyons on the third embassy; for when the representatives from
                              Oetaea went so far as to say that they ought to cast the grown men
                              over the cliffs, I brought the Phocians into the assembly of the
                              Amphictyons and secured a hearing for them. For Phalaecus had made
                              terms for himself and gone, and those who were guiltless were on the
                              point of being put to death; but I pleaded for them, and their lives
                              were spared.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="143" type="section">
                        <p> To prove that I speak the truth, please call Mnason the Phocian and
                              those who have come with him, and call the delegates chosen by the
                              Boeotian exiles. Come up to the platform, Liparus and Pythion, and do
                              me the same service for the saving of my life that I did for
                                    you.<quote type="Plea of the Boeotians and Phocians"><title>Plea
                                          of the Boeotians and Phocians</title></quote><milestone
                                    unit="para" ed="P"/>Would it not, then, be monstrous treatment
                              for me if I should be convicted when my accuser is Demosthenes, the
                              paid servant of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> and
                              the wickedest man in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>,
                              while my advocates are Phocians and Boeotians?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="144" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But he dared to say that I am tripped up
                              by my own words. For he says<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><bibl
                                          n="Dem. 19.243">Dem. 19.243</bibl> f.</note> that when I
                              was prosecuting Timarchus I said that his lewdness was a matter of
                              common report, and that Hesiod, a good poet, says, “But Common Report
                              dies never, the voice that tongues of many men do utter. She also is
                                    divine.”<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><bibl
                                          n="Aeschin. 1.129">Aeschin. 1.129</bibl>.</note> He says
                              that this same god comes now and accuses me, for everybody says,
                              according to him, that I have got money from Philip.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="145" type="section">
                        <p> But be assured, fellow citizens, there is the greatest difference
                              between common report and slander. For common report has no affinity
                              with malice, but malice is slander's own sister. I will define each of
                              them specifically: it is a case of common report when the mass of the
                              people, on their own impulse and for no reason that they can give, say
                              that a certain event has taken place; but it is slander when one
                              person, insinuating an accusation in the minds of the people,
                              calumniates a man in all the meetings of the assembly and before the
                              senate. To Common Report we offer public sacrifice, as to a god, but
                              the slanderer we prosecute, in the name of the people, as a scoundrel.
                              Do not, therefore, join together the most honourable and the most
                              shameful things.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="146" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>At many of his charges I was indeed angry,
                              but most of all when he accused me of being a traitor. For to bring
                              such charges as those was to hold me up to public view as a brute,
                              without natural affection, and chargeable in the past with many other
                              sins. Now of my daily life and conduct I think you are competent
                              judges. But facts that escape the public eye, yet are of greatest
                              importance in the opinion of men of character, I will bring into court
                              as my witnesses—facts very many in number and to my credit in the eyes
                              of the law—in order that seeing them you may know what pledges I left
                              at home when I set out for <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                                    >Macedonia</placeName> on the embassy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="147" type="section">
                        <p> For you, Demosthenes, fabricated these charges against me, but I will
                              tell my story, as I was taught to do from childhood, truthfully.
                              Yonder is my father, Atrometus; there are few older men among all the
                              citizens, for he is now ninety-four years old. When he was a young
                              man, before the war destroyed his property, he was so fortunate as to
                              be an athlete; banished by the Thirty, he served as a soldier in
                                    <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, and in danger he
                              showed himself a man; by birth he was of the phratry<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">Each of the four Athenian tribes was divided
                                    into three phratries. Under the democracy these groups of
                                    families had only religious functions. Each phratry had its own
                                    place of worship.</note> that uses the same altars as the
                              Eteobutadae, from whom the priestess of Athena Polias comes; and he
                              helped in the restoration of the democracy, as I said a little while
                                    ago.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <bibl
                                          n="Aeschin. 2.78"> Aeschin. 2.78</bibl>.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="148" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It is my good fortune, too, that all the
                              members of my mother's family are free-born citizens; and to-day I see
                              her here before my eyes in anxiety and fear for my safety. And yet,
                              Demosthenes, this mother of mine went out to <placeName
                                    key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> an exile, with her
                              husband, and shared the disasters of the democracy; but you, who claim
                              to be a man—that you really are a man I should not venture to say—you
                              were once indicted for desertion, and you saved yourself by buying off
                              the man who indicted you, Nicodemus of Aphidna, whom afterward you
                              helped Aristarchus to destroy;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><p>In
                                          the spring of 348 Demosthenes was serving on an expedition
                                          sent out to <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
                                                >Euboea</placeName>. On the approach of the Great
                                          Dionysia he was obliged to return to the city to serve as
                                          choragus, a burden which he had previously volunteered to
                                          take upon himself, at heavy cost. Personal enemies of his
                                          brought, but did not prosecute, a charge of desertion in
                                          the field.</p><p>The murder of Nicodemus by Aristarchus, a
                                          young friend of Demosthenes, was a notorious case, but the
                                          attempts of Demosthenes' enemies to connect him with it
                                          were entirely unsuccessful. See <bibl n="Aeschin. 1.172"
                                                >Aeschin. 1.172</bibl>.</p></note> wherefore you are
                              polluted, and have no right to be invading the market-place.<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A man under indictment for murder
                                    was not allowed access to the market-place, for contact with a
                                    murderer would pollute innocent men.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="149" type="section">
                        <p> Philochares yonder, our eldest brother, a man not of ignoble pursuits,
                              as you slanderously assert,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For
                                    Demosthenes' taunts as to the brothers of Aeschines and those of
                                    his wife, see his speech <bibl n="Dem. 19.237">Dem.
                                          19.237</bibl> and 287.</note> but a frequenter of the
                              gymnasia, a one-time comrade of Iphicrates in the field, and a general
                              now for the past three years, has come to beg you to save me. Our
                              youngest brother, too, Aphobetus yonder, who as ambassador to the king
                              of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> has served you to
                              the credit of the city, who administered your revenues honestly and
                              well when you called him to the department of the treasury, who has
                              gotten him children lawfully—not by putting his wife in Cnosion's bed,
                              as you, Demosthenes, did yours—he also is here, despite your slanders
                              ;for defamation goes no further than the ears.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="150" type="section">
                        <p> But you dared to speak about my wife's family also—so shameless you are
                              and so inherently thankless, you that have neither affection nor
                              respect for Philodemus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <bibl
                                          n="Aeschin. 2.152">Aeschin. 2.152</bibl>.</note> the
                              father of Philon and Epicrates, the man by whose good offices you were
                              enrolled among the men of your deme, as the elder Paeanians know.<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Aeschines insinuates that only by
                                    some extraordinary favoritism could Demosthenes, with his strain
                                    of Scythian blood, ever have been recognized as an Athenian of
                                    pure blood, and so enrolled in the citizen-list when he came to
                                    manhood.</note> But I am amazed if you dare slander Philon, and
                              that, too, in the presence of the most reputable men of Athens, who,
                              having come in here to render their verdict for the best interest of
                              the state, are thinkingmore about the lives we have lived than what we
                              say.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="151" type="section">
                        <p>Which think you would they pray heaven to give them, ten thousand
                              hoplites like Philon, so fit in body and so sound of heart, or thrice
                              ten thousand lewd weaklings like you? You try to bring into contempt
                              the good breeding of Epicrates, Philon's brother; but who ever saw him
                              behaving in an indecent manner, either by day in the Dionysiac
                              procession, as you assert, or by night? For you certainly could never
                              say that he was unobserved, for he was no stranger.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="152" type="section">
                        <p> And I myself, gentlemen, have three children, one daughter and two sons,
                              by the daughter of Philodemus, the sister of Philon and Epicrates; and
                              I have brought them into court with the others for the sake of asking
                              one question and presenting one piece of evidence to the jury. This
                              question I will now put to you; for I ask, fellow citizens, whether
                              you believe that I would have betrayed to Philip, not only my country,
                              my personal friendships, and my rights in the shrines and tombs of my
                              fathers, but also these children, the dearest of mankind to me. Do you
                              believe that I would have held his friendship more precious than the
                              safety of these children? By what lust have you seen me conquered?
                              What unworthy act have I ever done for money? It is not <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName> that makes men good or
                              bad, but their own inborn nature; and we have not come back from the
                              embassy changed men, but the same men that you yourselves sent
                              out.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="153" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But in public affairs I have become
                              exceedingly entangled with a cheat and rascal, who not even by
                              accident can speak a truthful word. No: when he is lying, first comes
                              an oath by his shameless eyes, and things that never happened he not
                              only presents as facts, but he even tells the day on which they
                              occurred; and he invents the name of some one who happened to be
                              there, and adds that too, imitating men who speak the truth. But we
                              who are innocent are fortunate in one thing, that he has no
                              intelligence with which to supplement the trickery of his character
                              and his knack of putting words together. For think what a combination
                              of folly and ignorance there must be in the man who could invent such
                              a lie against me as that about the Olynthian woman,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">See <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.4">Aeschin. 2.4</bibl>,
                                    note.</note> such a lie that you shut him up in the midst of his
                              speech. For he was slandering a man who is the farthest removed from
                              any such conduct, and that in the presence of men who know.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="154" type="section">
                        <p> But see how far back his preparations for this accusation go. For there
                              is a certain Olynthian living here, Aristophanes by name. Demosthenes
                              was introduced to him by some one, and having found out that he is an
                              able speaker, paid extravagant court to him and won his confidence;
                              this accomplished, he tried to persuade him to give false testimony
                              against me before you, promising, namely, to give him five hundred
                              drachmas on the spot, if he would consent to come into court and
                              complain of me, and say that I was guilty of drunken abuse of a woman
                              of his family, who had been taken captive; and he promised to pay him
                              five hundred more when he should have given the testimony.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="155" type="section">
                        <p> But Aristophanes answered him, as he himself told the story, that so far
                              as his exile and present need were concerned, Demosthenes' aim had not
                              been wide of the mark—indeed no aim could have been closer—but that he
                              had entirely misjudged his character; for he could do nothing of the
                              sort. I will offer Aristophanes himself to testify to the truth of
                              what I say. Please call Aristophanes the Olynthian, and read his
                              testimony, and call those who heard his story and reported it to
                              me—Dercylus, of the deme Hagnus, the son of Autocles, and Aristeides
                              of Cephisia, the son of Euphiletus.<quote type="Testimony"
                                          ><title>Testimony</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="156" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You hear the sworn testimony. But these
                              wicked arts of rhetoric, which Demosthenes offers to teach our youth,
                              and has now employed against me, his tears and groans for <placeName
                                    key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, and his praise of Satyrus
                              the comic actor, because over the cups he begged of Philip the release
                              of certain friends of his who were captives in chains, digging in
                              Philip's vineyard—you remember, do you not, how after this preface he
                              lifted up that shrill and abominable voice of his and cried out,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="157" type="section">
                        <p> “How outrageous that when a man whose business it is to act the parts of
                              a Carion or of a Xanthias<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Satyrus,
                                    the comic actor, would often take slave parts, for which Carion
                                    and Xanthias were among the traditional names.</note> showed
                              himself so noble and generous, Aeschines, the counsellor of the
                              greatest city, the adviser of the Ten Thousand of <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>, did not restrain his
                              insolence, but in drunken heat, when Xenodocus, one of the picked
                              corps of Philip, was entertaining us, seized a captive woman by the
                              hair, and took a strap and flogged her!”</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="158" type="section">
                        <p> If you had believed him, or Aristophanes had helped him out in his his
                              against me, I should have been destroyed under shameful accusations.
                              Will you therefore harbour longer in your midst guilt that is so
                              fraught with doom to itself—God grant it be not to the city!—and will
                              you, who purify your assembly,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                                    Athenian assembly was regularly opened with a sacrifice of
                                    purification and prayer.</note> offer the prayers that are
                              contained in your decrees on motion of this man, as you send your
                              troops out by land or sea? You know the words of Hesiod:<cit>
                                    <quote type="verse"><l met="u">“Ofttimes whole peoples suffer
                                                from one man</l><l>Whose deeds are sinful and whose
                                                purpose base.”</l></quote>
                                    <bibl>Hes. WD 240</bibl>
                              </cit></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="159" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>One thing more I wish to add to what I
                              have said: if there is anywhere among mankind any form of wickedness
                              in which I fail to show that Demosthenes is preeminent, let my death
                              be your verdict. But I think many difficulties attend a defendant: his
                              danger calls his mind away from his anger, to the search for such
                              arguments as shall secure his safety, and it causes him earnest
                              thought lest he overlook some one of the accusations which have been
                              brought against him. I therefore invite you, and at the same time
                              myself, to recall the accusations.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="160" type="section">
                        <p> Consider, then, one by one, fellow citizens, the possible grounds for my
                              prosecution: what decree have I proposed, what law have I repealed,
                              what law have I kept from being passed, what covenant have I made in
                              the name of the city, what vote as to the peace have I annulled, what
                              have I added to the terms of peace that you did not vote?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="161" type="section">
                        <p> The peace failed to please some of our public men. Then ought they not
                              to have opposed it at the time, instead of putting me on trial now?
                              Certain men who were getting rich out of the war from your war-taxes
                              and the revenues of the state, have now been stopped; for peace does
                              not feed laziness. Shall those, then, who are not wronged, but are
                              themselves wronging the city, punish the man who was sponsor for the
                                    peace,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Philocrates, the prime
                                    mover in the peace had already gone into banishment, afraid to
                                    stand trial.</note>1 and will you, who are benefited by it,
                              leave in the lurch men who have proved themselves useful to the
                              commonwealth?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="162" type="section">
                        <p> Yes, my accuser says, because I joined Philip in singing paeans when the
                              cities of <placeName key="tgn,4003963">Phocis</placeName> had been
                                    razed.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><bibl n="Dem. 19.128"
                                          >Dem. 19.128</bibl></note> What evidence could be
                              sufficient to prove that charge? I was, indeed, invited to receive the
                              ordinary courtesies, as were my colleagues in the embassy. Those who
                              were invited and were present at the banquet, including the
                              ambassadors from other Hellenic states, were not less than two
                              hundred. And so it seems that among all these I was conspicuous, not
                              by my silence, but by joining in the singing—for Demosthenes says so,
                              who was not there himself, and presents no witness from among those
                              who were.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="163" type="section">
                        <p> Who would have noticed me, unless I was a sort of precentor and led the
                              chorus? Therefore if I was silent, your charge is false; but if, with
                              our fatherland safe and no harm done to my fellow citizens, I joined
                              the other ambassadors in singing the paean when the god was being
                              magnified and the Athenians in no wise dishonored, I was doing a pious
                              act and no wrong, and I should justly be acquitted. Am I, forsooth,
                              because of this to be considered as a man who knows no pity, but you a
                              saint, you, the accuser of men who have shared your bread and cup?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="164" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But you have also reproached me with
                              inconsistency in my political action, in that I have served as
                              ambassador to Philip, when I had previously been summoning the Greeks
                              to oppose him.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <bibl n="Dem. 9.9"
                                          >Dem. 9.9</bibl> ff.</note> And yet, if you choose, you
                              may bring this charge against the rest of the Athenian people as a
                              body. You, gentlemen, once fought the Lacedaemonians, and then after
                              their misfortune at Leuctra you aided the same people. You once
                              restored Theban exiles to their country, and again you fought against
                              them at <placeName key="tgn,7010918">Mantineia</placeName>. You fought
                              against Themison and the Eretrians, and again you saved them. And you
                              have before now treated countless others of the Hellenes in the same
                              way. For in order to attain the highest good the individual, and the
                              state as well, is obliged to change front with changing
                              circumstances.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="165" type="section">
                        <p> But what is the good counsellor to do? Is he not to give the state the
                              counsel that is best in view of each present situation? And what shall
                              the rascally accuser say? Is he not to conceal the occasion and
                              condemn the act? And the born traitor—how shall we recognize him? Will
                              he not imitate you, Demosthenes, in his treatment of those whom chance
                              throws in his way and who have trusted him? Will he not take pay for
                              writing speeches for them to deliver in the courts, and then reveal
                              the contents of these speeches to their opponents?<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">Cp. <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.173">Aeschin.
                                          3.173</bibl>.</note> You wrote a speech for the banker
                              Phormion and were paid for it: this speech you communicated to
                              Apollodorus, who was bringing a capital charge against Phormion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="166" type="section">
                        <p> You entered a happy home, that of Aristarchus the son of Moschus; you
                              ruined it. You received three talents from Aristarchus in trust as he
                              was on the point of going into exile;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                                    >The occasion was the murder of Nicodemus by Aristarchus. See
                                          <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.148">Aeschin. 2.148</bibl>,
                                    note.</note> you cheated him out of the money that was to have
                              aided him in his fight, and were not ashamed of the reputation to
                              which you laid claim, that of being a wooer of the young man's bodily
                              charms—an absurd story, of course, for genuine love has no place for
                              rascality. That conduct, and conduct like that, defines the
                              traitor.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="167" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But he spoke, I believe, about service in
                              the field, and named me “the fine soldier.” But I think, in view of my
                              present peril rather than of his slander, I may without offence speak
                              of these matters also. For where, or when, or to whom, shall I speak
                              of them, if I led this day go by? As soon as I passed out of boyhood I
                              became one of the frontier guards of this land for two years.<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">the young Athenian citizen, coming
                                    of legal age at eighteen, was required to serve two years in the
                                    cadet corps, stationed the first year at the Peiraeus, and on
                                    frontier posts the second.</note> As witnesses to this
                              statement, I will call my fellow cadets and our officers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="168" type="section">
                        <p> My first experience in the field was in what is called “division
                                    service,”<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">When citizens were
                                    called out for military service, if it was not necessary to call
                                    the whole body of reserves, the men of some specified age were
                                    called. e.g. all between the ages of twenty and thirty, or
                                    twenty and forty (cp. <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.133">Aeschin.
                                          2.133</bibl>). Since the names of the men of a given age
                                    were kept in the register under the name of the Archon Eponymos
                                    in whose year they came of age, such a levy was called <foreign
                                          xml:lang="greek">stratei/a e)n toi=s
                                    e)pwnu/mois</foreign>. If only a part of such an age-group was
                                    called out, it was called a division levy (<foreign
                                          xml:lang="greek">stratei/a e)n toi=s
                                    me/resin</foreign>).</note> when I was with the other men of my
                              age and the mercenary troops of Alcibiades, who convoyed the provision
                              train to Phleius. We fell into danger near the place known as the
                              Nemean ravine, and I so fought as to win the praise of my
                                    officers.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In 363 b.c. See <bibl
                                          n="Xen. Hell. 7.2.17">Xen. Hell. 7.2.17</bibl> ff.</note>
                              I also served on the other expeditions in succession, whether we were
                              called out by age-groups or by divisions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="169" type="section">
                        <p> I fought in the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010918"
                                    >Mantineia</placeName>, not without honour to myself or credit
                              to the city. I took part in the expeditions to <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">In 357 and 349/8.</note> and at the battle of
                                    <placeName key="perseus,Tamynae">Tamynae</placeName><note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The critical engagement of the
                                    second of the expeditions to <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
                                          >Euboea</placeName>.</note> as a member of the picked
                              corps I so bore myself in danger that I received a wreath of honour
                              then and there, and another at the hands of the people on my arrival
                              home; for I brought the news of the Athenian victory, and Temenides,
                                    taxiarch<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Each of the ten
                                    taxiarchs commanded the hoplites of a single tribe.</note> of
                              the tribe Pandionis, who was despatched with me from camp, told here
                              how I had borne myself in the face of the danger that befell us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="170" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But to prove that I am speaking the truth,
                              please take this decree, and call Temenides and those who were my
                              comrades in the expedition in the service of the city, and call
                              Phocion, the general, not yet to plead for me,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">Phocion will later he called to support the
                                    prayer of the defence for acquittal.</note> if it please the
                              jury, but as a witness who cannot speak falsely without exposing
                              himself to the libellous attacks of my prosecutor.<quote type="Decree"
                                          ><title>Decree</title></quote><quote type="Testimony"
                                          ><title>Testimony</title></quote></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="171" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Since, then, it was I who brought you the
                              first news of the victory of the city and the success of your sons, I
                              ask of you this as my first reward, the saving of my life. For I am
                              not a hater of the democracy, as my accuser asserts, but a hater of
                              wickedness; and I am not one who forbids your “imitating the
                              forefathers” of Demosthenes<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <bibl
                                          n="Dem. 9.16">Dem. 9.16</bibl>.</note>—for he has none—but
                              one who calls upon you to emulate those policies which are noble and
                              salutary to the state. Those policies I will now review somewhat more
                              specifically, beginning with early times.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="172" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>In former days, after the battle of
                                    <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, our city stood
                              in high repute, and although our walls had been thrown down by the
                              barbarians, yet so long as we had peace with the Lacedaemonians we
                              preserved our democratic form of government.<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">Aeschines has taken the historical review which
                                    he gives in <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.172">Aeschin. 2.172-176</bibl>
                                    from the speech of Andocides, <title> On the Peace with the
                                          Lacedaemonians</title> (<bibl n="Andoc. 3.3">Andoc.
                                          3.3</bibl> ff.) , condensing, and changing the phraseology
                                    at will, and changing the application of the facts which he
                                    cites. This sketch as given by Andocides is characterized by
                                    Eduard Meyer (<title>Forschungen zur Alten Geschichte,</title>
                                    2.132 ff.) as a caricature of the actual course of events,
                                    valuable only as a convincing proof of the untrustworthiness of
                                    oral tradition, and of the rapidity and certainty with which
                                    confusion and error as to historical facts develop, even in the
                                    mind of a contemporary who has had a prominent part in the
                                    events.</note> But when certain men had stirred up trouble and
                              finally caused us to become involved in war with the Lacedaemonians,
                              then, after we had suffered and inflicted many losses, Miltiades, the
                              son of Cimon, who was proxenus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                                    proxenus was a citizen who was employed by a foreign state to
                                    represent its interests in his own state.</note> of the
                              Lacedaemonians, negotiated with them, and we made a truce for fifty
                              years, and kept it thirteen years.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                                    >This was in fact a five years' truce negotiated by Cimon, the
                                    son of Miltiades, in 450 b c. The truce lasted, not thirteen
                                    years, but less than five. The fortification of the Peiraeus
                                    belongs more than a quarter of a century earlier.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="173" type="section">
                        <p> During this period we fortified the Peiraeus and built the north wall;
                              we added one hundred new triremes to our fleet; we also equipped three
                              hundred cavalrymen and bought three hundred Scythians;<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A corps of bowmen, Scythian slaves,
                                    owned by the state and used as city police.</note> and we held
                              the democratic constitution unshaken.<milestone unit="para" ed="P"
                              />But meanwhile men who were neither free by birth nor of fit
                              character had intruded into our body politic, and finally we became
                              involved in war again with the Lacedaemonians, this time because of
                              the Aeginetans.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The war with
                                          <placeName key="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName> ended
                                    before the above-mentioned truce began.</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="174" type="section">
                        <p> In this war we received no small injury, and became desirous of peace.
                              We therefore sent Andocides and other ambassadors to the
                              Lacedaemonians and negotiated a peace, which we kept for thirty
                                    years.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The thirty years' peace
                                    was in fact made in 446/5, and was kept only fifteen
                                    years.</note> This peace brought the democracy to the height of
                              its prosperity. For we deposited on the Acropolis a thousand talents
                              of coined money we built one hundred additional triremes, and
                              constructed dockyards; we formed a corps of twelve hundred cavalry and
                              a new force of as many bowmen, and the southern long wall was built;
                              and no man undertook to overthrow the democratic constitution.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="175" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But again we were persuaded to go to war,
                              now because of the Megarians.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                                    beginning of the Peloponnesian war, 431 b.c.</note> Having given
                              up our land to be ravaged, and suffering great privations, we longed
                              for peace, and finally concluded it through Nicias, the son of
                                    Niceratus.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The “Peace of
                                    Nicias” was negotiated in 421, but its terms were only partially
                                    fulfilled from the beginning, and very soon the war was in full
                                    operation again. Andocides places in this period, which he
                                    falsely assumes to be one of peace, events that belong to the
                                    Periclean period.</note> In the period that followed we again
                              deposited treasure in the Acropolis, seven thousand talents, thanks to
                              this peace, and we acquired triremes, seaworthy and fully equipped, no
                              fewer than three hundred in number; a yearly tribute of more than
                              twelve hundred talents came in to us; we held the <placeName
                                    key="tgn,1012789">Chersonese</placeName>, <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7012053">Naxos</placeName>, and <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, and in these years we sent
                              out a host of colonies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="176" type="section">
                        <p> Though the blessings we were enjoying were so great, we again brought
                              war against the Lacedaemonians, persuaded by the Argives;<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                          >Athens</placeName> entered into alliance with <placeName
                                          key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, <placeName
                                          key="tgn,7010918">Mantineia</placeName>, and <placeName
                                          key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName> in 420. This
                                    immediately reopened the war with the Lacedaemonians.</note> and
                              at last, in consequence of the eagerness of our public men for war, we
                              sank so low as to see a Spartan garrison in our city, and the Four
                              Hundred, and the impious Thirty;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                                    oligarchy of the Four Hundred was the result of the revolution
                                    of 411 b.c. The rule of the Thirty Tyrants followed the
                                    surrender of the city at the close of the Peloponnesian war. The
                                    Thirty were supported by a Spartan garrison (404-403).</note>
                              and it was not the making of peace that caused this,<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true">The setting up of the Thirty was dictated by
                                          <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>.</note>
                              but we were forced by orders laid upon us. But when again a moderate
                              government had been established, and the exiled democracy had come
                              back from <placeName key="perseus,Phyle">Phyle</placeName>,<note
                                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName key="perseus,Phyle"
                                          >Phyle</placeName>, a post on the Boeotian frontier, was
                                    the rallying point of the band of exiles who began the movement
                                    for the expulsion of the Thirty</note> with Archinus and
                              Thrasybulus as the leaders of the popular party, we took the solemn
                              oath with one another “to forgive and forget” an act which, in the
                              judgment of all men, won for our state the reputation of the highest
                              wisdom.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="177" type="section">
                        <p> The democracy then took on new life and vigour. But now men who have
                              been illegally registered as citizens, constantly attaching to
                              themselves what ever element in the city is corrupt, and following a
                              policy of war after war, in peace ever prophesying danger, and so
                              working on ambitious and over excitable minds, yet when war comes
                              never touching arms themselves, but getting into office as auditors
                              and naval commissioners—men whose mistresses are the mothers of their
                              offspring, and whose slanderous tongues ought to disfranchise
                              them—these men are bringing the state into extreme peril, fostering
                              the name of democracy, not by their character, but by their
                              flatteries, trying to put an end to the peace, wherein lies the safety
                              of the democracy, and in every way fomenting war, the destroyer of
                              popular government.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="178" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>These are the men who now are making a
                              concerted attack on me; they say that Philip bought the peace, that he
                              overreached us at every point in the articles of agreement, and that
                              the peace which he contrived for his own interests, he himself has
                              violated. And they put me on trial, not as an ambassador, but as a
                              surety for Philip and the peace; the man who had nothing but words
                              under his control they call to account for deeds—deeds that existed
                              only in their own imagination. And the very man whom I exhibit to you
                              as my eulogist in the public decrees, I have found as my accuser in
                              the court-room. And although I was but one of ten ambassadors, I alone
                              am made to give account.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="179" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>To plead with you in my behalf are present
                              my father, whom I beg of you not to rob of the hopes of his old age;
                              my brothers, who would have no desire for life if I should be torn
                              from them; my connections by marriage; and these little children, who
                              do not yet realize their danger, but are to be pitied if disaster fall
                              on us. For them I beg and beseech you to take earnest thought, and not
                              to give them over into the hands of our enemies, or of a creature who
                              is no man—no better in spirit than a woman.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="180" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>And first of all I pray and beseech the
                              gods to save me, and then I beseech you, who hold the verdict in your
                              hands, before whom I have defended myself against every one of the
                              accusations, to the best of my recollection; I beg you to save me, and
                              not give me over to the hands of the rhetorician and the Scythian. You
                              who are fathers of children or have younger brother's whom you hold
                              dear, remember that to me they are indebted for a warning which they
                              will not forget, admonished to live chastely through my prosecution of
                              Timarchus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="181" type="section">
                        <p> And all the rest of you, toward whom I have conducted myself without
                              offence, in fortune a plain citizen, a decent man like any one of you,
                              and the only man who in the strife of politics has refused to join in
                              conspiracy against you, upon you I call to save me. With all loyalty I
                              have served the city as her ambassador, alone subjected to the clamour
                              of the slanderers, which before now many a man conspicuously brave in
                              war has not had the courage to face; for it is not death that men
                              dread, but a dishonoured end.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="182" type="section">
                        <p> Is he not indeed to be pitied who must look into the sneering face of an
                              enemy, and hear with his ears his insults? But nevertheless I have
                              taken the risk, I have exposed my body to the peril. Among you I grew
                              up, your ways have been my ways. No home of yours is the worse for my
                              pleasures; no man has been deprived of his fatherland by accusation of
                              mine at any revision of the citizen-lists, nor has come into peril
                              when rendering account of his administration of an office.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="183" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>A word more and I have done. One thing was
                              in my power, fellow citizens: to do you no wrong. But to be free from
                              accusation, that was a thing which depended upon fortune, and fortune
                              cast my lot with a slanderer, a barbarian, who cared not for
                              sacrifices nor libations nor the breaking of bread together; nay, to
                              frighten all who in time to come might oppose him, he has fabricated a
                              false charge against us and come in here. If, therefore, you are
                              willing to save those who have laboured together with you for peace
                              and for your security, the common good will find champions in
                              abundance, ready to face danger in your behalf.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="184" type="section">
                        <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>To endorse my plea I now call Eubulus as a
                              representative of the statesmen and all honourable citizens, and
                              Phocion as a representative of the generals, preeminent also among us
                              all as a man of upright character. From among my friends and
                              associates I call Nausicles, and all the others with whom I have
                              associated and whose pursuits I have shared.<milestone unit="para"
                                    ed="P"/>My speech is finished. This my body I, and the law, now
                              commit to your hands.</p>
                  </div>

            </body>
      </text>
</TEI>
